<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The principles of law reduced to practice. By W. Phillipps.</title>
            <author>Phillipps, W.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 160 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 103 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90662</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2058</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1905_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210006</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868847</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868847</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170545</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90662)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170545)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 236:E1905[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The principles of law reduced to practice. By W. Phillipps.</title>
                  <author>Phillipps, W.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[36], 167, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Hen. Twyford, Thomas Dring, and Iohn Place, and are to be sold at their shops,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Feb:".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Law --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Legal maxims --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170545:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PRINCIPLES OF LAW Reduced to PRACTICE.</p>
            <p>By W. PHILLIPPS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Hen. Twyford, Thomas Dring, Iohn Place,</hi> and are to be ſold at their Shops, 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170545:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170545:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Midſt the many Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints that have been taken up againſt the <hi>Law,</hi> there is not any that ſeems of <hi>Weight,</hi> unleſſe it be that of it's want of <hi>Method.</hi> And in truth that is not a <hi>real,</hi> but only a <hi>ſeeming</hi> Objection: for the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned know that the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>England</hi> (excepting
<pb facs="tcp:170545:3"/>Statutes) is a <hi>cuſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and no <hi>written</hi> Law: and therefore it is no wonder, that the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors</hi> thereof have not been curious in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodizing of that <hi>Art,</hi> which has it's force onely from <hi>Cuſtome,</hi> and was never committed to <hi>wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</hi> But, although it be not capable of <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite Method;</hi> it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be denyed, but of late times, fair <hi>Eſſayes</hi> have been made for the better retaining of the ſame in <hi>memory:</hi> which has bin by putting <hi>particular Caſes</hi> under <hi>generall
<pb facs="tcp:170545:3"/>Rules;</hi> which, as to the <hi>younger</hi> Students it muſt needs be very <hi>help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful;</hi> ſo, to <hi>Atturneys</hi> (whoſe practiſe will not permit them to peruſe the greater Volumes of the Law,) it cannot be leſſe <hi>uſefull.</hi> Having therefore at <hi>ſpare hours</hi> Collected the Enſuing <hi>Principles of Law,</hi> and communicated the ſame to ſome moſt <hi>emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent</hi> in that <hi>Profeſſion;</hi> their <hi>approbation</hi> has been ſuch, that it has deemed them worthy the <hi>Publique view.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon being ſecured of the
<pb facs="tcp:170545:4"/>skil of thoſe <hi>Gentlemen</hi> I confidently commit them to the <hi>World,</hi> not doubting but they will have as good reception abroad, as they have met with in private. For, if I miſtake not much, you will find them to come home to your <hi>Buſineſs</hi> and <hi>Occaſions.</hi> Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="maxims">
            <pb facs="tcp:170545:4"/>
            <head>A TABLE Of the MAXIMS, Diſplayed in this <hi>TRACTATE.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <head>A</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>ACceſſorium non ducit ſed ſequitur ſuum Principale.</hi> The Acceſſory followeth the Principal: fol. 1.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170545:5"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>A communi obſervantiâ non eſt recedendum.</hi> Common opinion, a rule in Law. fol. 2.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Actio perſonalis moritur cum per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſona.</hi> A perſonal action ends with the perſon. Ibid.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Actus Dei nemini facit injuriam.</hi> An act of God injureth no man. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Actus legis nulli facit injuriam.</hi> An act of Law is injurious to none. fol. 3</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Actus non facit reum niſi mens ſit rea.</hi> The mind, not the act, maketh a man guilty. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Actus repugnans non poteſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duci in eſſe.</hi> Contradictions cannot be brought into being ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Actus me in vito factus non eſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us actus.</hi> An act done againſt my will, is not my act: fol. 4</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Actori incumbit onus probandi:</hi> The Plaintiff muſt prove. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Additio probat minoritatem.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170545:5"/>
               <item>Addition argues the leſſe extent. fol. 5.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ad proximum antecedens fiat re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latio.</hi> The Relative has reſpect to the next Antecedent. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ad quaeſtionem Facti non reſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Judices.</hi> Judges do not decide matters of fact. fol. 6</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Aeſtimatio praeteriti delicti poſt factum munquam creſcit.</hi> No ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent matter adds degrees of guilt to a paſt fault. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Affectio no men imponit operi.</hi> The intention denominates the action. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Affectus punitur, licet non ſequatur effectus.</hi> The affection is puniſhable, though the effect do not follow. fol. 7</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Affirmativum negativum impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat.</hi> An affirmative implyeth a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Agentes &amp; Conſentientes pari poenâ plectuntur.</hi> The actor and the
<pb facs="tcp:170545:6"/>conſentor are equally culpable. fol. 8.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Aliquis non poteſt eſſe Iudex in propria cauſa.</hi> None muſt be judge in his own cauſe. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Apices juris non ſunt jura.</hi> Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Law are no Law. fol. 9</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ambiguum placitum interpretari debet contra proferentem.</hi> A doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full plea ſhall be taken ſtrongeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the pleader. ib.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>B</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Benignae faciendae ſunt interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationes chartarum, propter ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem laicorum; ut res magis valeat quam pereat.</hi> Charters admit of a favourable conſtruction, by reaſon of the Lay mans ignorance; that the thing may be in force rather then periſh. fol. 10.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Benignior ſenſus in verbis dubiis eſt praeferendus.</hi> In doubtfull
<pb facs="tcp:170545:6"/>things, the moſt favourable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction is to be preferr'd. 11.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>C</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cauſa &amp; origo est materia negotii.</hi> The cauſe of the buſineſs is the offence of it. 11.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Caveat emptor.</hi> Let the buyer beware. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Certa debet eſſe intentio &amp; nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio.</hi> Counts and Declarations ought to be certain. 12</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ceſſante cauſa, ceſſat effectus.</hi> The cauſe being gone, the effect ceaſeth. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Charta non eſt niſi vestimentum donationis.</hi> Charter is, as it were, the garment of the gift. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Communis error facit jus.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon error conſtituteth a right. 13.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Conſenſus, non concubitus, facit
<pb facs="tcp:170545:7"/>matrimonium.</hi> Conſent, not the ſheets compleats the marriage. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Conditio bene ficialis quae statum construit, benigne ſecundum vrbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum intentionem eſt interpretanaa</hi>-Beneficial conditions are to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken according to the intention of the words. 14</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Conſenſus tollit errorem.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent takes away error. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Conſuetudo debet eſse certa.</hi> A cuſtome ought to be certain. 15</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Conſtructio juris nemini facit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juriam.</hi> Favourable conſtruction of Law injures no man. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Conſuetudo ſemel reprobata non poteſt amplius introduci.</hi> A cuſtome once rejected cannot be uſed again. 16</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Conſuetudo tollit legem.</hi> Cuſtom taketh away the Law. 17</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Contraria aellegans non est audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endus.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:170545:7"/>He that alledgeth contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions is not to be heard. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cui licet quod majus eſt, non debet quod minus eſt non licere.</hi> He that may doe more, can doe leſſe. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cuique naturale eſt, illud quod procreavit tueri.</hi> The Law of Nature commands every one to defend his iſſue. 18</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cuilibet in arta ſua perito eſt credendum.</hi> The Artiſt muſt be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved in his own Art. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cujus est dare, ejus est diſponere.</hi> The Giver may diſpoſe of his gift. ib.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>D</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Debile fundamentum tollit opus.</hi> A weak foundation defeats the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtructure. 19</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Derivativa potestas non poteſt eſſe
<pb facs="tcp:170545:8"/>major primitivâ</hi> A derivative po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer cannot be greater then the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive. 20</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Deſtinata tantum, pro factis non habentur.</hi> Things intended ſhall not be taken for things done, ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>De fide &amp; offieio Iudicis, non re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitur quaeſtio.</hi> A Judge's honeſty ought not to be queſtioned. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dies Dominicus non eſt juridieus.</hi> The Sabbath-day is no day in Law. 21</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Divinatio, non interpretatio est, quae omnino recedit à litera.</hi> It is a gueſſing, not an interpretion, which wholly leaves the Letter. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dilationes in lege ſunt odioſae.</hi> Dilatory pleas are odious. 22</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dispoſitio de intereſſe futuro, eſt inutilis.</hi> A diſpoſition of a future in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt is null. ib.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170545:8"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dominus non maritabit minorem in cuſtodia ſua, niſi ſemel.</hi> A Ward ſhall be forced to marriage but once. 23</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dormit aliquando jus, moritur nunquam.</hi> A right is ſuſpended ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, never extinguiſhed. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Doti mulieris parcatur, quia prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mium pudoris eſt.</hi> A womans dower ſhall be ſpared, becauſe it is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of chaſtity. 24</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dona clandeſtina ſemper ſunt ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitioſa.</hi> Under board gifts are ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picious. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dos de dote peti non debet.</hi> One Dower cannot be made out of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Eccleſia fungitur vice minoris; meliorem poteſt facere conditionem, deteriorem nequaquam.</hi> The Church
<pb facs="tcp:170545:9"/>exerciſing the office of a minor, it may make his condition better, not worſe: 25</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Executio juris nulli facit injuram.</hi> Execution of the Law injures none. 26</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Expreſſio eorum quae tacite inſunt, nihil operatur.</hi> Expreſſion of thoſe things which are underſtood works nothing: ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ex nudo pacto non oritur actio.</hi> Of a bare agreement there ariſeth no action. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Expreſſum facit ceſſare tacitum.</hi> An expreſs drowneth an implicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. 27</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Extra juriſdictionem jus dicenti, non paretur impune.</hi> He that obeys a Judg beyond his commiſſion, ſhall not go Scot-free. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Exteriora acta indicant interiora animi ſecreta:</hi> The outward actions ſhew the inward intentions of the mind: ib.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170545:9"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ex verbo gencrali aliquid exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitur.</hi> Every general rule has an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception. 28.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Facinus quos inquinat aequat.</hi> An offence equalleth thoſe that are guilty of it. 28</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Festinatio Juſtitiae noveroe infortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nii.</hi> More haſte then good ſpeed. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Finis rei attendendus,</hi> Mark the end. 29</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Filiatio non poteſt probari.</hi> Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timation cannot be proved. 30</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Firmior eſt operatio legis quam diſpoſitio hominis.</hi> The diſpoſition of the Law is ſtronger than any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſo of man: ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fruſtra fit per plura, quod poteſt fieri per pauciora.</hi> Much is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, where leſſe will ſerve the
<pb facs="tcp:170545:10"/>turn. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Furioſus furore ſuo punitur.</hi> A mad-man is puniſhed by his own madneſs. 31.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>G</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Generale nihil oerti implicat.</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals determine nothing. 32.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Generalibus ſemper ſpecialia inſunt</hi> Special things are alwayes contained in generals. 32.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Generalis clauſula non refertur ad expreſſa.</hi> A general clauſe is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to thoſe things which are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. 33.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Generalis clauſula non porrigitur ad ea, quae antea ſunt ſpecialiter comprehenſa.</hi> A general clauſe is not extended to thoſe things, which were before ſpecially comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. 34.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Generalia ſunt praeponenda ſingula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus.</hi> Generals are to be preferred
<pb facs="tcp:170545:10"/>before particulars. ib.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>H</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Haeres eſt pars anteceſſoris.</hi> The ſon is part of the father. 35.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Haeres legitimus, eſt, quem nup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae demonſtrant.</hi> He is a lawfull heir, whom marriage connteth ſo: ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Haeres non tenetur ad debita ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſoris reddenda, niſi per anteceſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem ad hoc ſuerit obligatus; praeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam debita Regis tantum.</hi> An heir is not bound to pay his anceſtor's debts, unleſſe to the King, if he be not bound by the deed of his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtor. ib:</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hermaphrodita tam maſculo quam foeminae comparatur, ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum praevaleſcentiam ſexus incaleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centis.</hi> An Hermaphrodite inherits, according to the prevalency of the ſex. 36.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:170545:11"/>
               <head>I</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Id certum eſt, quod certum reddi poteſt.</hi> That is certain, that may be made certain. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ignoratio Iuris non excuſat.</hi> Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of the Law is no excuſe. 37</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ignorantia facti execuſat.</hi> Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the fact does excuſe. 38</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ignoratis terminis, ignoratur &amp; ars.</hi> The terms not known, the art is not underſtood. 38</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Impotentia ex uſat legem.</hi> That which cannot be helpt, cannot hurt. 39</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Idem non poteſt eſſe agent &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiens.</hi> The ſame cannot be agent and patient. ib:</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Imperſonalitas nec concludit, nec ligat.</hi> Imperſonality doth not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude nor bind. 40</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Imperitia maximae eſt mechani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum
<pb facs="tcp:170545:11"/>poena.</hi> Ignorance is the artiſts greateſt puniſhment. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Incluſio uninus eſt excluſio alteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</hi> The including of one thing is the excluding of another. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Infinitum in jure reprobatur.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity is rejected in Law: 41</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>In fictione legis ſemper eſt aequitas.</hi> In the fiction of Law is quity. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>In aequali jure melior eſt poſſeſſio poſſidentis.</hi> In an equall cauſe poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion is beſt. 42</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Injuria illata in corpus non poteſt remitti.</hi> Injuries made upon the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy cannot be remitted, ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>In ambiguis caſibus, ſemper prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumitur pro Rege.</hi> In ambiguous ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, 'tis alwayes preſumed for the King. 43</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>In disjunctivis, ſufficit alterum eſſe verum:</hi> In disjunctives, 'tis ſufficient if one of them be true: ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>In jure, non remota ſed proxima
<pb facs="tcp:170545:12"/>cauſa ſpectatur.</hi> The Law reſpects the moſt immediate cauſe. 44.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Impoſſibile eſt unum corpus in duo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus locis eſſe ſimul.</hi> The ſame body cannot be at two places at the ſame time. 46.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>In praeſentia majoris, ceſſat poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia minoris.</hi> A greater power drowns a leſs. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>In quo quis deliquit, in eo de jure puniendus eſt.</hi> In what one offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, in the ſame he rightly ſuffers. 47</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>In omnibus obligationibus, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus dies non ponitur, praeſenti die de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betur.</hi> Where no time is ſet, the debt is preſently due. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Judic is eſt judicare ſecundum al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legata &amp; probata.</hi> The Judge ought to determine according to proof. 48.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Judicium pro veritate accipitur.</hi> Judgment &amp; truth equivalent: ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Judicium a non ſuo judice datum,
<pb facs="tcp:170545:12"/>nullius eſt momenti.</hi> If Judgment be not given by the proper Judge, it is of no force. 49</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Junior non poteſt dotem promereri.</hi> A woman under nine years cannot have dower. 50</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jura naturalia ſunt immutabilia.</hi> The Laws of nature are immutable. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ipſae etenim leges eupiunt ut jure regantur.</hi> Laws are ruled by equity: 51</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jura publica anteferenda priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</hi> Publick rights are to be prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before private. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jus accreſcendi praefertur oneribus.</hi> Right of increaſe is preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore charge. 52.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ius accreſcendi praefertur ultimae voluntati.</hi> The right of Encreaſe is preferred before the laſt Teſtament. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ius deſcendit &amp; non terra.</hi> Right, not the Land deſcendeth. 53.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170545:13"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Juſtum non eſt, aliquem ante ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonium natum, mortuum, facere baſtardum, qui toto tempore ſuo pro legitimo habebatur.</hi> It is unjuſt to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke him a baſtard, when dead; who was accounted legitimate while alive. ib.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>L</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lex eſt ſumma ratio.</hi> The Law is the perfection of Reaſon. 54</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Licet Tenenti vetus opus reficere, non novum facere.</hi> The Tenant may repair, cannot build. 55</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lex non praecipit inutilia.</hi> The Law preſcribeth not in vain. 56</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lex ſemper intendit quod convenit rationi.</hi> The Intendment of the Law is alwayes conſonant to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. 57</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lex ſpectat naturae ordinem.</hi> The Law regardeth the order of nature. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lex non cogit ad impoſſibilia.</hi> The Law forceth not to things impoſſible 58.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170545:13"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lex libertati das favorem:</hi> The Law favours liberty. 58</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lex citius tolerare vult privatum damnum, quam publicum malum.</hi> The Law will ſooner tolerate a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate injury, than a publick inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience. 59</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Liberata pecunia non liberat effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentem.</hi> Money tendered does not diſcharge the Obligor. 60</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Linea recta ſemper praefertur tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſali.</hi> A right line is alwayes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before a collateral. 61</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>M</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mala Grammatica non vitiat char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam.</hi> Falſe Latine doth not deſtroy a Deed. 61</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Maritus &amp; uxor, animae duae ſunt in una carne:</hi> Man and wife are two ſouls in one fleſh: 62.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Malus uſus abolendus.</hi> An evill uſage is to be aboliſhed: 63</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Maxime paci contraria ſunt vis &amp; injuria.</hi> Violence is contradicto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Peace. ib.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170545:14"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Meliorem conditionem facere poteſt minor, deteriorem nequaquam.</hi> An Infant may better his condition, cannot make it worſe. 64</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Minor jurare non poteſt.</hi> An Infant cannot be upon his oath. 65</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Modus &amp; conventio vincunt le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem.</hi> An agreement doth alter the Law. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mulieres ad probationem ſtatus bominis admitti non debent.</hi> Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are not admitted to prove the condition of a man. 66</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Multa tranſeunt cum univerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litate, quae per ſe non tranſeunt.</hi> Many things paſs in a crowd, which do not paſſe in themſelves. ib.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>N</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Negatio nihil implicat.</hi> A nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive implyeth nothing. 67</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nemo debet bis puniri pro uno de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licte.</hi> None ought to be puniſhed twice for the ſame fault. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nemo potest plus juris in alium transferre quam ipſe habet:</hi> None
<pb facs="tcp:170545:14"/>can transfer a greater right, then he himſelf hath. 68</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Neminem oportet eſſe ſapientiorem legibus.</hi> None ought to aſpire to be wiſer then the Laws. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nemo tenetur exponere ſe inf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niis &amp; periculis.</hi> None is bound to expoſe himſelf to peril. 69</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nemo punitur pro aliens delicto.</hi> None ſuffers for anothers fault. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nemo tenetur prodere ſeipſum.</hi> No man is bound to betray himſelf. 70</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nihil quod eſt inconveniens val con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra rationem, eſt licitum.</hi> Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences are unlawful. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Non refert an quis aſſenſum praebe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at verbis aut factis.</hi> It matters not, whether an aſſent be by words or deeds. 72</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Non afficit con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tus, niſi ſequatur effectus.</hi> The endeavour ſignifies nothing, unleſs the effect follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. 73.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Non eſt haeres viventis:</hi> There is no actual heir of the living pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſor. 74</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170545:15"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Non valet pactum de re mea non alienanda.</hi> A contract, that I ſhould not alien what is my own, is of no validity. 75</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nullum iniquum in jure eſt prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumendum:</hi> No injuſtice is preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the Law. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nullum tempus occurrit Regi.</hi> No time prevaileth againſt the King.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nullum ſimile eſt idem.</hi> No like is the ſame. 76</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nullus commodum capere poteſt de injuria ſua propria.</hi> None can take advantage of his own wrong. 77</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>O</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Omnis privatio praeſupponit habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</hi> Every privation preſuppoſeth an habit. 78</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Omnia quae movent ad mortem ſunt Deodanda.</hi> All things which cauſe death are Deodands. 79</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Omne teſtamentum morte conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matum eſt.</hi> The death of the Devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor compleats the Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. ib.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170545:15"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Omne majus continet in ſe miuns:</hi> Every more containeth in it ſelfe a leſs. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Omnia quae ſunt uxoris, ſunt ipſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us viri.</hi> That which is the Wive's, is the Husband's. 80</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Omnis ratihabitio aequiparatur mandato.</hi> Every approve is equiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent to a command. 81</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Oportes ut res certa deducatur in judicium.</hi> It behoveth, that a thing certain ſhould be brought into judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. ib.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>P</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pater est quem nuptiae demonſtrant</hi> Marriage proves the father. 82</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pendente lite nihil innovetur.</hi> Writ hanging, nothing muſt be innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Perſpicue vera non ſunt probanda.</hi> Clear truths are not to be proved. 83</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Plus peccat author, quam actor.</hi> The author is more guilty then the inſtrument. 84</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170545:16"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Poſſeſio fratris de foedo ſimplici, facit ſororein elſe haeredem.</hi> The poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the brother of a fee ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, m keth the ſiſter to be heir. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Propinquior excludit propinquum.</hi> The nearer akin excludes the more remote. 85</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Proximus ſum egomet miki.</hi> I love my ſelf beſt. ib.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Q</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Quando lex aliquid concedit, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedere videtur &amp; id, ſine quo res eſse non poteſt.</hi> When the Law granteth any thing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> granteth that, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which the matter could not be. 86</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Quando aliquid fieri prohibetur ex directo, prohibetur &amp; per obliquum.</hi> A direct prohibition includes an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique one. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Quando jus Domini Regis &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diti concurrunt, jus Regis praeferri debet.</hi> When the right of the King and Subject ſtands in competition, the Kings is preferr'd. 87</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170545:16"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Quaelibet haereditas naturaliter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendit:</hi> Every inheritance does na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally deſcend. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Quae in partes dividi nequeunt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lida à ſingulis praeſtentur.</hi> Things entire muſt be entirely paid of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. 88</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Quaelibet conceſſio fortiſſime contra donatorem interpretanda eſt.</hi> Every Grant is to be taken moſt ſtrongly againſt the Grantor. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Qui non babet in are, luat in corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.</hi> Either the purſe paies, or the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſuffers. 89.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Qui ex damnato ccitu oriuntur, inter liberos non compusentur.</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards are not accounted amongſt ſons. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Qui haeret in litera, haeret in corti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce.</hi> He that ſticks in the letter, ſticks in the out-ſide. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Qui adimit medium, dirimit ſinem.</hi> He that takes away the means, takes away the end. 90</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Qui peccat ebrius, luat ſobrius.</hi> He
<pb facs="tcp:170545:17"/>that offends when he is drunk, ſhall ſuffer when he is ſober. 91</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Qui per alium facit, per ſeipſum fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere videtur.</hi> He that doth by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, doth by himſelf. 91</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Qui ſemel actionem renuntiavit, amplius repetere non poteſt.</hi> A re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traxit burs all actions. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Qui ſentit commodum, ſentire debet &amp; onus.</hi> He that beareth the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, ought to receive the profit. 92</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Quod ab initio non valet, traccu temporis non convaleſcet.</hi> That which is invalid in the beginning, tract of time will not make good. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Quod prius eſt tempore, potius eſt jure.</hi> Prioritie in time prevails in Law. 93</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Quod ſemel meum eſt, amplius me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um eſſe non poteſt.</hi> That which is once mine, cannot be twice mine. 94</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Quod ſemel placuit in electionibus, umplius diſplicere non poteſt:</hi> That which is preferred by election, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be altered. 95</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170545:17"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Quoties in verbis nulla eſt ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guitas, ibi nulla expoſitio contra verba expreſſa fienda eſt.</hi> Where there is no ambiguity in the words, there expreſs meaning ſhall be taken. 69</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Quod conſtat clare, non debet veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficari.</hi> Of that which is clear, no need of any averment. 97</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>R</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Refert, à quo fiat perquiſitum.</hi> It matters from whom the purchaſe comes. 98</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Remote impedimento, emergit actio.</hi> The impediment being removed, the action doth ariſe. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Repellitur à Sacramento infamis.</hi> A ſcandalous perſon is barr'd of his oath. 99</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Res inter alios acta alteri nocere non debet.</hi> A thing acted amongſt ſome, ought not to prejudice others. ib.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>S</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Senſus verborum ex cauſa dicendi accipiendus eſt.</hi> The ſence of the words is to be taken from the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb facs="tcp:170545:18"/>of the ſpeech. 100</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Semper praeſumitur pro legitima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione puerorum.</hi> Legitimation is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes preſumed. 101</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Si mulier nobilis nupſerit ignobili, deſinit eſſe nobilis.</hi> If a Noblewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man by marriage, marries under the degrees of Nobility, ſhe loſeth her Nobility. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Solus Deus facere poteſt her aedem.</hi> God alone can make an heir. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Stabitur preſumptioni donee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betur in contrarium:</hi> The preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is good, till the contrary be proved. 102</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>T</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Teſtamento cum duo inter ſe pug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantia reperiuntur, ultimum ratum eſt:</hi> The laſt taketh place. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Traditio loqui facis chartum.</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery makes the Deed valid. 103</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>U</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vana eſt potentia, quae nunquam venit in actum:</hi> That power is fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraneous, which is never produced into act. ib.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170545:18"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi non eſt principalis, ibi non pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt eſſe acceſſarius.</hi> Where there is no principal, there can be no acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary: 104</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi endem ratio, ibi idem jus.</hi> The ſame reaſon, the ſame Law. 105</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi nullum matrimonium, ibi nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la dos.</hi> No marriage, no dower. 106</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Verba accipienda ſunt in mitiori ſenſu.</hi> Words are to be taken in a favourable ſence. 107</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Verba ſunt accipienda cum effectu.</hi> Words are to be taken with the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Verba aquivoca intelliguntur dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niere ſenſu.</hi> Doubtful words are to be taken in the more worthy ſence. 108</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Verba rolat a hoe maxime operan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, per referentiam, ut in eſſe vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antur.</hi> Relative words do eſpecially work this by reference as they may ſeem in being. 109</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Verba chartarum fortius accipiun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur contra proferentem.</hi> The words
<pb facs="tcp:170545:19"/>of a Deed are moſt ſtrongly taken againſt the Grantor. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>numquodque diſſolvitur eo liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine quo ligatur:</hi> Every thing is diſſolved by the ſame it obliges. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltima voluntas teſtatoris perim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plendae est, ſecundum veram intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem:</hi> The Will of the Teſtator is exactly to be performed. 110</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>oluntas teſtatoris ambulatoria eſt uſque ad mortem:</hi> The laſt Wil on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtands. 111</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Volenti non fit injuria.</hi> To him that is willing, there is no injury done. ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tile per inutile non vitiatur.</hi> That which is profitable is not deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by that which is fruſtrane ous. 112.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xor non est ſui juris, ſed ſub poteſtate viri.</hi> The Wife has not her own ſwing, but is under the power of her husband:</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170545:19"/>
            <head>Law-Principles Reduc'd to Practice.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ACceſſorium non du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit ſed ſequitur ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Principale.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As if a man let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth Lands for life ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring certain rent, if he grant in Reverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to another, and the Tenant attorn, all the Rent and Service paſs by this word <hi>Reverſion;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Rent in ſuch caſe, is incident to the Reverſion. But albeit he
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170545:20"/>granteth the Rent to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother,<note place="margin">10 H. 7.10. Coke l. 5.21. Ployd. 235. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> the Reverſion doth not paſs by ſuch grant, <hi>Litt.</hi> 152. <hi>a.</hi> 33. <hi>H.</hi> 6.33.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A communi obſervantia non eſt recedendum.</hi> A com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon opinion is good au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in Law.<note place="margin">Lit. 186. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Coke:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Actio perſonalis moritur cum perſona.</hi> If a Leſſee for years doth waſte, and dyeth;<note place="margin">Litt 53. <hi>b.</hi> Dy. 114.</note> a Writ of waſte lieth not againſt his Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor or Adminiſtrator, for waſte done in his life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Actus Deinemini facit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juriam.</hi> As,<note place="margin">Cokel. 1.98. <hi>a.</hi> Coke l. 148. Coke l. 8.72.63. <hi>a.</hi> l. 5.86.</note> If a Leſſee co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant to leave the wood in as good a plight as it was at the time of the Leaſe; and after, the trees are ſubverted by tempeſts,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170545:20"/>he is diſcharged of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Actus Legis nulli facit injuriam.</hi> If Land, out of which Rent-charge is granted, be recovered by an older Title, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Rent-charge is avoided; yet the Grantee ſhall have a Writ of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity, for that the Rent-charge is avoided by the courſe of Law. <hi>Coke Lit.</hi> 148. a. 178. a <hi>Coke l.</hi> 5.87. <hi>Dy,</hi> 60.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Actus non facit reum, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi mens ſit rea.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in criminal Cauſes, as Felony, the Act and Wrong of a mad-man ſhal not be imputed to him. <hi>Lit. Com.</hi> 247. b. <hi>Doct. &amp; Stud.</hi> 148.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Actus repugnans non<note place="margin">Coke l. 1.</note>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:170545:21"/>poteſt in eſſe produci.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Corbet</hi>'s Caſe. Dy. 153.21. E. 436.4. E. 4.29.</note> 
                  <hi>Ployd.</hi> 255. <hi>a.</hi> As if a Gift in Tail, upon condition, that if the Donee aliene, that then it ſhall remain to another, it is repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; for, after aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it cannot remain. An Obligation, <hi>ſolvendum nunquam,</hi> the <hi>Solvendum</hi> is void for the contrarie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the thing preſently due.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Actus me invito factus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lit. Com. 253. <hi>b.</hi> 14. Aſſ. pl. 20.21: E. 4.28. Coke l. 2.9. Ployd. 18. <hi>a.</hi> Coke l. 4.70. Lit. Com. 233. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>non eſt meus.</hi> As, when one is compelled for fear of Impriſonment, to make a Bond, or other Deed; ſuch fear ſufficeth to avoid the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Actori incumbit onus probandi.</hi> Bargainee and Bargainee; if the Bargai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner intend to avoid
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170545:21"/>the Bargain, by reaſon of non-inrollment within ſix months; he muſt make manifeſt proof thereof, or elſe it will be preſumed, that it was inrolled.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Additio probat minori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem.</hi> When it is ſaid any where,<note place="margin">Lit. Com. 139. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> that a man is ſeized in Fee, it ſhall be intended Fee-ſimple, and not Fee-tail; unleſs there be added to it this additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Fee-tail.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ad proximum antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens fiat relatio.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 20. <hi>b.</hi> Dy. 14. <hi>b.</hi> 46. <hi>b.</hi> Coke. l. 2.71. <hi>Cromwel's</hi> Caſe.</note> If a man let Land to <hi>A.</hi> for life, the remainder to B. in Tail, the remainder to <hi>C in formâ praedictâ;</hi> this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder is void, for the uncertainty. But if the remainder had been to <hi>C. in eadem forma,</hi> this had
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170545:22"/>been a good Eſtate Tail; for, <hi>Idem ſemper proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo antecedenti refertur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ad quaeſtionem facti, non reſpondent Indiecs.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lit. Com. 155. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Ad quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionem Iuris, non reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Iuratores.</hi> The moſt u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual trial of matters of fact is, by twelve men. And matters in 'Law, the Judges ought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aeſtimatio praeteriti de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licti poſt factum nunquam creſcit.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">11 H. 4.12</note> If the Gaoler let the Parcuſſor voluntarily to go at liberty; and, after, the party wounded, dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; yet it is no feloninus eſcape.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Affectio nomen imponit operi.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lit. Com. 49. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> If it be agreed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Diſſeiſor and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170545:22"/>Diſſeiſed,<note place="margin">Ployd. 86. 141.21. H. 6.55. 1 E. 4.11. 4 E. 4.23.</note> that the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeiſed ſhall releaſe all his right to the Diſſeiſor up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Land; and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly the Diſſeiſed en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth into the Land, and delivereth the Releaſe to the Diſſeiſor upon the Land, This is a good Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe; and the Entry of the Diſſeizee being to this purpoſe, ſhall not avoid the Diſſeizin; for his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in this caſe did guide his Entry to a ſpecial pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Affectus punitur licet non ſequatur effectus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">34 H. 6.26.27. Aſſ. pl. 44.19. R. 2. Breife 726.</note> To give money to one retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned on the Jury, though he be not ſworn, is Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Affirmativum negati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum implicat.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 9.56.</note> As <hi>W.</hi> 2.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170545:23"/>2.6.11.<note place="margin">Weſtm. c. 3. 4. Ployd. 206. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> That upon account before Auditors, and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re-ages, they have power to ſend their Bodies to the next Gool of the Lord their King, in thoſe parts. Hence it is, that it is herd, 27: <hi>H.</hi> 6.8. That the Auditor ought to commit him to the next Gaol, though another County.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Agentes &amp; conſentien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes pari poena plectuntur.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">22. Aſſ. pl. 82. Coke l. 5.80. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>A.</hi> maimeth <hi>B.</hi> by the conſent of <hi>C.</hi> An Appeal lyeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>A.</hi> and <hi>C.</hi> and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages equally againſt both.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aliquis non poteſt eſſe Judex in propriâ cauſa.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 141. <hi>a.</hi> Coke l. 8.118. Dy. 65.12 H. 8.11</note> If one will preſcribe, that if any Cattle were upon the Demeans of the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, doing Damage;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170545:23"/>that the Lord of the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, for the time being, hath uſed to Diſtrein them, and the Diſtreſs to retain, till Fine made to him for the Damages, at his will; This preſcription is void: for ſo he ſhould be his own Judg:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Apices Juris non ſunt Jura.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 283. <hi>b.</hi> 304. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> The Law of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> reſpecteth the effect and ſubſtance of the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,<note place="margin">Coke l. 4.45. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> and not every Nicety of form or Circumſtance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ambiguum placitum interpretari debet contra proferentem.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> The Plea of every man ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued ſtrongly againſt him that pleadeth it; for every man is preſumed to make the beſt of his own caſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:170545:24"/>
               <head>B</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Benignae ſunt faciendae interpretationes Charta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lit. Com. 183. <hi>b.</hi> 112. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>propter ignorantiam laicorum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 3.25.</note> 
                  <hi>ut res magis va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leat quam pereat.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ployd. 197. <hi>b.</hi> 213. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>pereat.</hi> As, if Lands be given to two men, and to the Heirs of their two bodies begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; the Donors have a joynt-eſtate for term of their lives, and yet they have ſeverall inheritan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, inſomuch as they cannot by any poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, have an heir between them ingendred. The Law will, that their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate and Inheritance be ſuch, as is reaſonable, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the form and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170545:24"/>effect of the words of the Gift; and this is to the heirs which the one ſhall beget of his body, by any of his wives; and ſo of the other.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Benignior ſenſus in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis ganeralibus ſen dubiis eſt praeferendus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 4. fol. 15. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> As, if one charge another, that he hath forſworn himſelf, it is not Actionable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſhall be intended, to be forſworn in uſual communication. <hi>Coke l.</hi> 4.15.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>C.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cauſa &amp; origo eſt mate.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 1. <hi>Shelley</hi>'s caſe. Dy. 266. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ria negotii.</hi> If a Servant have an intent to kill his Maſter; and, before exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170545:25"/>of his intent, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteth out of his ſervice, and afterwards kills him: it is petty Treaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caveat emptor.</hi> If I ſell another man's Horſe,<note place="margin">Litt. 102. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> and he take him out of the Vndee's poſſeſſion; yet I ſhall have an action of debt for the mony.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Certa debet eſſe intentio &amp; narratio.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ployd. 84: <hi>a.</hi> 3. E. 4.21.</note> Debt, by one retained in Husbandry, againſt a Prioreſſe, for his Salary; and declares, that he was retain'd with her Predeceſſor, and doth not ſhew by what perſon; it ſhall abate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ceſſante cauſa ceſſat ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect us.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 6.13. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>on's</hi> caſe.</note> If the Lord marry the Heir female within the two years, which he hath to tender her Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170545:25"/>her Husband and ſhe ſhall preſently Enter. <hi>Litt.</hi> 78. b.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charta non eſt niſi ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimentum donationis.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ployd. 291.22. H. 6.10.</note> And therefore if the intent be performed, though not the words of the Deed, it ſufficeth:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Communis error facit jus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> &amp; <hi>Stud.</hi> 46. Ployd. 2. <hi>Manxel</hi>'s caſe.</note> As, an Acquittance by the Mayor alone, where there are many pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents for it, is good.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſenſus, non concubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, facit Matrimonium.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 5 fol. 22. Litt. 33. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> As, in <hi>Ambroſia Gorges</hi>'s caſe: ſhe married <hi>Francis Gorge,</hi> which <hi>Francis</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed when <hi>Ambroſia</hi> was often years of age. It was reſolved, that the Queen, notwithſtanding the ſaid marriage, ſhould have
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170545:26"/>the Wardſhip of the ſaid <hi>Ambroſia:</hi> For, it was not a compleat Marriage, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe to every Marriage there ought to be a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; and, <hi>Conſentire non poſſunt, ante annos nubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conditio Beneficialis quae ſtatum conſtruit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cokel. 8.90. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>benigué, ſecundum verborum inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dy. 45. p. 1. 7. E. 4.13.</note> 
                  <hi>eſt interpretanda; Odioſa tamen, quae statum deſtruit, ſtrictè ſecundum verborum proprietatem, eſt accipienda.</hi> A Leaſe to one upon condition, that the Leſſee ſhall not alien to <hi>A. B.</hi> and he alien to <hi>R. B.</hi> the condition is not broken; for every Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion muſt be taken ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſenſus tollit erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:170545:26"/>If a <hi>Venire facias</hi> be awarded to the Coroners,<note place="margin">Litt. 37. <hi>a.</hi> 126. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> where it ought to be to the Sheriff;<note place="margin">Coke l. 5. fol. 40.</note> or the <hi>Viſno</hi> come out of a wrong place; yet, if it be <hi>per aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſum partium,</hi> and ſo entred of Record, it ſhall ſtand.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſuetudo debet eſſe certa.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">13. E. 2. <hi>Fit</hi> a. <hi>Dum fuit infra aetatem,</hi> 3.</note> In Treſpaſſe for Trees carried away, the Defendant pleaded a Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, that that Tenant of the Mannor, that firſt came to the place where, &amp;c. ſhall have the Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falls there: Void, for the uncertainty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Constructio Iuris nemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni facit injuriam.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. 18.3. <hi>a. b.</hi>
                  </note> It is a Rule, that whenſoever the words of a Deed,<note place="margin">Coke l. 3.74.</note> or of the Parties without Deed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <note place="margin">Ployd. 77. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:170545:27"/>ſhall have a double in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendment, and the one ſtandeth with Law, and Right, and the other not; that that ſtandeth with Law ſhall be taken.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſuetudo ſemel repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bata, non poteſt amplius in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduci.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. 114. <hi>b</hi>
                  </note> As, if a Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold be Leaſed of the Lord of the Mannor, for Life, or Years, according to the courſe of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law, it ſhall never be after demiſed by cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, as a Copy-hold. For, as continuance ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a cuſtome, ſo diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance deſtroyeth it. But a Title gained by preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion cannot be loſt by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruption of Poſſeſſion, but by interruption in the Right.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:170545:27"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſuetudo tollit com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munem legem.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. 33. <hi>b.</hi> 158. <hi>b.</hi> Coke. l. 4.21. Ployd. 36. <hi>b.</hi> vid. <hi>Stat. de conſuetud. Kanciae.</hi>
                  </note> By the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of <hi>Gavelkind,</hi> the Wife ſhall be endowed of the Moiety, ſo long as ſhe keeps her ſelfe ſole, and without child; which ſhe cannot wave, and take her Thirds for her life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Contraria allegans non eſt Audiendus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">21. H. 7.21.</note> As, in pleading Guilty to the breaking of the Houſe, and Not-guilty to the Walls, in Treſpaſſe, <hi>de domo fractâ &amp; muris e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſdem domi;</hi> It is not good.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cui licet quod majus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 9.23. <hi>a.</hi> l. 9.48. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>non debet quod minus eſt non licere.</hi> Where Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold Lands may, by cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the Mannor, be granted to any one in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170545:28"/>Fee-ſimple; there, a Grant to one, and the heirs of his body, is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Cuſtom.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cuique naturale eſt, id quod procreavit tueri.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ployd. 304. <hi>a.</hi> 11. H. 4.23.33. H.6.55.12. <hi>H.</hi> 4.16.</note> And therefore is given to the Father, the education and cuſtody of his Son; and, if any take him from him, he ſhall have a Writ, <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re filium &amp; haeredem ſuum rapuit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cuilibet, in arte ſua pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rito, eſi credendum.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lit. 125. <hi>a.</hi> Coke l. 4.29. <hi>a.</hi> l. 7.19. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> In Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence given in Cauſes in the Spirituall Court, the Judges of the Common Law, though it be againſt the Reaſon of the Law, ſhall give faith and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to their Procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cujus eſt dare, ejus eſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170545:28"/>diſponere.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> fol. 70.</note> That a <hi>Proviſo</hi> make a Condition,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cromwel</hi>'s caſe.</note> three thing are required; Firſt, That the <hi>Proviſo</hi> do not depend upon another Sentence, nor participate thereof; but ſtand origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally of it ſelf. Secondly, That the <hi>Proviſo</hi> be the word of the Bargainor, Foeffor, Donor, &amp;c. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, That it be compulſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to enforce the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainee, Foeffee, Donee, Leſſee, &amp;c. to do an Act, and where theſe concur, it is a Condition, in what place ſoever it be placed. For, <hi>Cujus eſt dare, ejus eſt diſponere:</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>D.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Debile fundamentum fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit<note place="margin">Coke l. 6.14. <hi>a.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:170545:29"/>opus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">20. Aſſ. pl. 7.49. E. 3.8.3. E. 3.74.</note> When an Eſtate, to which a Warranty is annexed, is defeated; the Warranty alſo is defea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Derivativa poteſtas non poteſt eſſe major primitivâ.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">28 Aſſ. pl. 4.</note> The Bayliff of a Diſſeiſor ſhall not ſay, that the Plaintiff ever had any thing in the Land; for the Maſter himſelfe ſhall not have that plea, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is not Tenant of the Free-shold:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deſtinata tantum pro factis non habentur.</hi> As if I ſquare a Tree to make a Beam of a Houſe, and die before it be laid in the building; it ſhall go to the Executors.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>De fide &amp; officio Judicis non recipitur quaestio,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">F. N. B. f. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>ſed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170545:29"/>de ſcientia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3 H. 6.3.8 H. 6.23.5. E. 4.3. F.N.B. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>ſive error ſit Juris, ſive Facti.</hi> As, If I aſſign for Error, that whereas the Verdict paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for me, the Court re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it contrary, and ſo gave Judgement againſt me; This ſhall not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dies Dominicus non eſt Juridicus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dy: 168.</note> A <hi>Scire Facias</hi> out of the Common-Bench, Error aſſigned, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Teſt of it was upon a <hi>Sunday;</hi> and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged Error, becauſe no Law-day.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Divinatio non interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio eſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt.</note> 
                  <hi>quae omnino recedit a litera.</hi> As, If I have a Fee farm Rent of 10 <abbr>s.</abbr> iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing out of White-Acre; and, reciting the ſame Reſervation, grant
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170545:30"/>to <hi>J. S.</hi> a Rent of 5 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> to be received out of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Rent, and out of all my Lands and Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in Dale, with clauſe of Diſtreſs; it is void, becauſe it is againſt the words; and the copu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the words ſhew, the taking of them in an other ſenſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dilationes ſunt in lege odioſae.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ployd. 75. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> Though Warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are favoured in Law,<note place="margin">F.N.B. 178 W. 2. <hi>c.</hi> 25. Ployd. 98. <hi>a.</hi> 90.8.8 H. 7.8.</note> yet none ſhall vouch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one in Aſſize, if he be not preſent. And Dilatory Pleas muſt be good to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry common intent.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ployd. <hi>Ryder</hi>'s caſe.</note>
                  <hi>Diſpoſitio de intereſſe fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turo, eſt inutilis.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">19 H. 6.62. Dy. 221. pl. 18.90. pl. 8.</note> If I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe the Mannor of <hi>D.</hi> by ſpecial name, of which, at that time, I am not ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170545:30"/>and, after, I purchaſe it; if I make not ſome new publication of my Will, my Deviſe is void.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dominus non maritabit minorem in cuſtodia ſua,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lit. Com. 79. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>niſi ſemel.</hi> If the Guardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, in Chivaky, marry the Ward within the age of 14 years; and if after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, at the age of 14 years, he diſagree to the marriage, the Guardian ſhall not make tender of a ſecond marriage.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dormit aliquando jus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lit. Com. 279. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>moritur nunquam.</hi> For, of ſuch an high eſtimation is Right, in the eye of the Law, as the Law preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth it from death and deſtruction: When it is ſaid, that a Releaſe of Right doth in ſome ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170545:31"/>inure by way of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhment; it is to be underſtood, in reſpect of him that makes the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doti mulieris pareatur quia proemium pudoris eſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lit. Com. 31. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> Tenant in Dower ſhall not be diſtreined for the debt due to the King,<note place="margin">F. N. B. 150.</note> by the Husband in his life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, in the Lands which ſhe had in Dower.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dos de dote peti non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lit. Com. 31. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> The Father dyeth, and the Wife of the Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father is endowed of one Acre, and dyeth, The Wife of the Father ſhall be endowed onely of the two Acres reſidue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dona clandestina ſemper ſunt ſuſpicioſa.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke: l. 3.81. l. <hi>b.</hi> 72. <hi>Burrel</hi>'s caſe.</note> The Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignment of the Leaſe was
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170545:31"/>taken to be fraudulent; becauſe deliver'd in a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret manner to a perſon of mean quality.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>E</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eccleſia fungitur vice minoris;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 141. <hi>a.</hi> 103. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>meliorem poteſt facere conditionem, deterio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem nequaquam.</hi> A per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may have an action of waſte, and it ſhall be ſaid, <hi>Ad exhaere dationem eccleſiae.</hi> So if he make a leaſe for Life, he ſhall have a <hi>Conſimili caeſu,</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the life of the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee; but a perſon cannot make a diſcontinuance; but if he do and dye, his ſucceſſor may enter, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the diſconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:170545:32"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Executio juris nulli fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit injuriam.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 161. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> Therefore a man ſhall not be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for ſuing of Writs in the Kings Court,<note place="margin">Hob. 266. 1. Dy. 285. Pl. 37.</note> be it of right or wrong.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Expreſſio eorum quae taci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te inſunt nihil operatur.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 299. <hi>a.</hi> 30 Aſſ. pl. 8.1.7. E. 3.7. Coke l. 4.73.</note> As if a man ſeized of Land, letteth the ſame by Deed indented for years, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring a certain rent, with clauſe of diſtreſſe; this clauſe is vain, for the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor may diſtrain of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon right for the rent behinde.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ex nudo pacto non oritur actio.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 47. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> And therefore, in an action of debt for rent, it is a good plea for the Leſſee to ſay, that the Leſſor had nothing in the Tenement at the time
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170545:32"/>of the Leaſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Expreſſum facit ceſſare tacitum.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 210 <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> As if the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon a mortgage be to pay to the Mortgagee or his heirs,<note place="margin">Coke Rep. <hi>Altham</hi>'s caſe.</note> the money, &amp;c. and before the day of payment,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bedel</hi>'s caſe.</note> the Mortga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gee dieth, the Feoffor can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not pay the money to the Executors of the Mortga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gee.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Extra juriſdictionem jus dicenti,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">22 E. 4.33 Dy. 60. Pl. 26.14. H. 8.16.</note> 
                  <hi>non paretur impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</hi> When the proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are <hi>coram non judice,</hi> an action lies againſt them that execute the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exteriora acta indicant interiora animi ſecreta.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 100. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> When Licenſe is given to any one by the Law,<note place="margin">Coke l. 8.146. l. 9.59.</note> and he doth amiſs, be
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170545:33"/>ſhall be a treſpaſſer from the beginning.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ex verbo generali ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid excipitur.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 47. <hi>a.</hi> Ployd. 361. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> An ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception is part of the thing granted, and in <hi>eſſe,</hi> (as <hi>exceptis, ſalvo, praeter,</hi>) and out of a generall a part may be excepted.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>F</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Facinus quos inquinat, aequat.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">40. Aſſ. Pl. 25.</note> A ſervant procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth another to kill his Maſter; this is not petty Treaſon in the ſervant, becauſe but felony in the other.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Feſtina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>io Iuſtitiae nover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca infortunii.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nov. Int.</hi> 285. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,<note place="margin">Heb. 133. Litt. 304.</note> the Judges alwayes in caſes of Demurrers, have a time to conſider of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170545:33"/>the matter in doubt, by a <hi>Curia adviſare vult.</hi> And when judgement is given, it is, <hi>Et ſuper hoc viſis praemiſſis, &amp; per Juſticia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rios hic plenius intellectis,</hi> (and then, <hi>Ideo conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt.</hi>) As in the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment between the King and the Prior of <hi>Worce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> concerning an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriation. <hi>Et examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, &amp; intellectis, recordo et proceſſu coram toto Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilio, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Finis rei attendendus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 5. 87.</note> The end and fruit of a Suit, is ſatisfaction:<note place="margin">14 H. 7.8.33. H. 6.47.</note> but execution of the body is no ſatisfaction, but a gage for the debt. And therefore, after his death he ſhall reſort to another execution.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:170545:34"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Filiatio non poteſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bari.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 126. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> A man leaveth his wiſe enſeint with a child: iſſue ſhall not be taken that ſhe was not enſeint by her Husband on the day of his death; for, <hi>Filiatio non poteſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bari.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firmior eſt operatio legis quam diſpoſitio hominis.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 224. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> A Leaſe upon condition,<note place="margin">Coke l. 10.67. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> that if the Leſſee make any waſte,<note place="margin">37 H. 6.16.</note> a re-entry; if a ſtranger doth waſte,<note place="margin">Dy. 281. Doct. &amp; ſtud. l. 2. c. 4.</note> he may re-enter: Yet if the Tenant had been bound in an obligation that he ſhall do no waſte, he ſhall not forfeit his Bond by the waſte of a ſtranger.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fruſtra ſit per plura, quod fieri poteſt per paucio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 6.167. <hi>a.</hi> Ployd. 191. <hi>b.</hi> 9 H. 7.24.</note> If the King by his
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170545:34"/>Patent, reciting the eſtate tail, grant the reverſion, and further grant the Lands in poſſeſſion, thoſe ſeveral Grants in one Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent are as ſtrong in Law, as if the King by one Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent had recited the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate tail, and granted the reverſion, and by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother patent the Lands in poſſeſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Furioſus furore ſuo pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitur.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com 247. <hi>b.</hi> Ployd. 19. <hi>a.</hi> Litt. 124. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> And therefore if a Mad man commit Felony, he ſhall not dye for it: for though he hath broken the words of the Law, yet he hath not broken the Law.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:170545:35"/>
               <head>G</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Generale nil certum im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicat.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 2. fol. 33. <hi>Dodding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi> lib. 8.98. <hi>a. Baſpoles</hi> caſe.</note> If a man be bound to be Non ſuited in all actions that he hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another in the common Bench, he may ſay that he hath no action therein: otherwiſe, if the condition be particular, <hi>viz.</hi> that he ſhall be non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuited in a <hi>Formedon.</hi> So in arbitrement when the ſubm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſion is general, an award of one cauſe, though there were more between them, is good.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Generalibus ſemper ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialia inſunt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ployd. 467. <hi>b.</hi> 68. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> As the Stat. of <hi>Glouceſter</hi> giveth an action of waſt againſt him which holdeth for years,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170545:35"/>which is in the plurall number, yet it may be taken for him that hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for a year, or half a year.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Generalis clauſula ad expreſſa non refertur.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 4. fol. 80. <hi>Noke</hi>'s Caſe.</note> An Aſſignee of a leaſe, ſhall have a Writ of Covenant upon the words, Demiſe and Graunt: yet if there be an expreſſe Covenant that the Leſſee ſhall enjoy it without eviction of the leſſor, or any claiming un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him, this expreſs co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant qualifieth the generality of the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in Law, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraineth it by mutuall conſent of both parties, that it ſhall not extend to the Aſſignee.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:170545:36"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Generalis clauſula non porrig itur ad ea,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 4.131. Dy. 56.6.</note> 
                  <hi>quae antea ſunt ſpicialiter comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa.</hi> When a deed at firſt contains ſpecial words, and then concludeth in words general, both ſhall ſtand: As Lands given to one and the heirs of his body, <hi>habendum</hi> to him and his heirs, he hath an eſtate tail, and a fee ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple expectant.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Generalia ſunt praepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenda ſin gularibus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>z Nat. B ev. 2. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> As in a Writ or Plaint, the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral ſhall be put in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand before the ſpecial, as Meſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>age before lands, Lands before Meadow, Mendow before Paſture, Paſture before Wood, Wood before Jancary, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:170545:36"/>
               <head>H.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Haeres eſt pars anteceſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lit. Com. 22. <hi>b.</hi> Coke l. 7.12.10 H. 7.8. Dy. 868. Kep. 151.</note> And therefore if Lands be given to a man and his heirs, all his heirs are ſo totally in him as he may give the Lands to whom he will.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Haeres legitimus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 7.44. <hi>a.</hi> Litt. 7.6.</note> 
                  <hi>eſt quem nuptiae demonſtrant.</hi> One who is ingendred in a vowtry during the cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is a Mulier by the temporal and common Law.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Haeres non tenetur ad debita anteceſſoris redden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Britton</hi> fol. 65. <hi>b.</hi> Litt. Com. 209. <hi>a.</hi> 383. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>niſi per anteceſſorem ad hoc fuerit obligatus; praeterquam debita regis tantum.</hi> If the heir be not named in the obligation,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170545:37"/>he ſhall not be bound by the deed of his Anceſtor, except to the King.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hermaphrodita tam maſculo quam faeminae,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 8. <hi>a. g. b.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratur ſecundum praeva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſcentiam ſexus incaleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centis.</hi> An Hermaphro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite ſhall be heir either as male or female, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that kind of the ſex which doth prevail; and accordingly it ought to be baptized.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>I</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Id certum eſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 45. <hi>b.</hi> 43. <hi>b.</hi> 96. <hi>a.</hi> Ployd. 273. <hi>b.</hi> Dy. 91. <hi>b.</hi> 44. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>quod cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum reddi poteſt.</hi> Albeit, there appear no certainty of years in a leaſe, yet if by reference to a certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it may be made cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, it ſufficeth. As a
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170545:37"/>leaſe to <hi>A.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">11 H. 11. 7.17.</note> for ſo many years as <hi>B.</hi> ſhall name: when <hi>B.</hi> hath named the years, it is a good leaſe for ſo many.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Idem ſemper proximo antecedenti refertur.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 20. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> As if a man let Lands to <hi>A.</hi> for life, the remainder to <hi>B.</hi> in taile, the remainder to <hi>C. in forma praedicta,</hi> this remainder is void for the incertainty: But if it had been the remainder to <hi>C. in eadem forma,</hi> this had been a good eſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ignorantia juris non ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſat.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> &amp; St. 2. c. 46. Coke l. 1. fol. 177. <hi>Mildmay</hi>'s Caſe.</note> If a ſtatute penall be made, and it is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted that the ſtatute ſhall be proclaimed by ſuch a day in every Shire, and it is not proclaimed before
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170545:38"/>the day: yet if any offend againſt this ſtatute, he ſhall not be excuſed for the not proclaiming of it; for he is bound to take notice of the Law at his peril.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ignorantia facti excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſat.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 2. fol. 3. <hi>b.</hi> Mauſer. Doct. &amp; Stud. l. 2. c. 47. 31 E. 3.3.</note> As if an illiterate man be bound to ſeal a Deed, he is not tyed to do it, if there be not ſome preſent to read it, if re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired; or, if it be read amiſſe, he may plead <hi>non eſt factum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ignoratis terminis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke Lit. 177. <hi>a.</hi> 2. <hi>a.</hi> 68. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur &amp; ars.</hi> Every art hath its <hi>vocabula artis,</hi> which being not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, that art cannot be comprehended. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſignifications of words in all arts and ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170545:38"/>are neceſſary, which Maſter <hi>Littleton</hi> and <hi>Coke</hi> upon him ordinarily ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Impotentia excuſat le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke Litt. 29. <hi>a.</hi> 258. <hi>b.</hi> 263. <hi>b.</hi> Coke Rep. <hi>Laughter</hi> caſe. Coke l. 98.</note> A man ſeized of an advowſon, or rent in fee, hath iſſue a daughter who is married, and hath iſſue, and dies ſeized; the wife before the rent became due, or the Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came void, dieth; ſhe had but a ſeizin in Law, and yet he ſhall be tenant by the courteſie, becauſe he could by no induſtry attain to any other ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zin.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Idem non poteſt eſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gens &amp; patiens.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">14 H. 8.31. 13 H. 8 32. 8 H. 6.29. 9 L. 4.32. Dye. 188.</note> And therefore a man cannot preſent himſelf to a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice. No man can ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170545:39"/>himſelf. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if a Sheriff ſuffer a common recovery, it is error, becauſe he cannot ſummon himſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Imperſonalitas non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludit nec ligat.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke Lit. 352. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore every <hi>Eſtoppell</hi> ought to be a preciſe affirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Imperitia maxima eſt maechanicorum poena.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">7 E. 3.65. <hi>b.</hi> Coke l. 11.57. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if he that taketh up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him to work be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilful and ignorant, it is ſufficient puniſhment for him: for if any take upon him to work and doth it amiſs, an action of the caſe lyeth againſt him:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Incluſio unius eſt exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio alterius.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lit. Com. 210. <hi>a</hi> Coke l. 11.50.</note> A morgage with the money to be
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170545:39"/>paid to the Morgagee and his heirs,<note place="margin">Ployden. 106.</note> it ſhall not be paid to his Executors.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Infinitum in jure repro batur.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 6.45. l. 7.456. l. 8.16. <hi>b.</hi> 3 H. 4.17.11. H. 4.9.9 E. 4.50, 51.</note> As if a man have a debt by a ſimple contract, and taketh an obligation for the ſame debt, or any part of it, the contract is determined: So of a Judgement upon an obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In fictione legis ſemper eſt aequitas.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com: 150. a. Coke l. 11.46. <hi>Liford's</hi> caſe.</note> As if one ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in Fee, take Wife, and make a Feoffment in Fee, the Feoffee grants a Rent-charge of 10 l. to the Feoffer and his Wife, and the heirs of the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band; the Husband dieth, the Wife recovereth the moity for her Dower by the Cuſtome; the Rent
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170545:40"/>ſhall be apportioned, and ſhe may diſtrain for five pound, which is the moity: for albeit the Dower by fiction of Law be above the Rent, yet when ſhe recovereth Dower, ſhe ſhall not have the entire Rent but of the reſidue: for fiction of Law ſhall never work a wrong to a third per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In aequali jure, melior eſt conditio poſſidentis.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">9 H. 5.15. Coke l. 4.90. <hi>a.</hi> l. 2.68. Perk. fol. 6.</note> If a man purchaſe ſeverall Lands at one time, which are holden of ſeverall Lords by Knights ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and dieth, the Lord who firſt ſeizeth the Ward ſhall have him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Injuria illata in corpus non poteſt remitti.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">I itt. Com. 1 27. <hi>a.</hi> 1 61. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Vita &amp;
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170545:40"/>membra ſunt in manu re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis.</hi> 19 <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. <hi>rotul.</hi> 36: And therefore if a Lord Mayheme his villain, the King ſhall puniſh him for mayming his Subjects, by Fine, Ranſome, and impriſonment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In ambiguis caſibus ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per praeſumitur pro rege.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">22. Aſſ. pl. 19. Stamf. fol 10.</note> And the reaſon that Treaſure Trove belongs to the King, is, <hi>Quia do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus rei non apparet; &amp; ideo cujus ſit incertum eſt,</hi> and therefore preſumed it is the Kings.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In disjuctivis ſufficit alterum eſſe verum.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 10.59. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Sarum</hi>'s caſe: Whereas the Avowant did avow that the Office <hi>ſupraviſoris omnium mane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riorum ſuorum,</hi> to ſuch
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170545:41"/>Perſon or Perſons as it pleaſed the Biſhop, and the Defendant pleaded in the negative, that the Office had not been but for the life of one; that exception was not allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, becauſe he did not ſay, that the ſaid Office had been granted to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, but only to ſuch perſon or perſons; and in disjunctives, it is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent that one of them be true.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In jure, non remota ſed proxima cauſa ſpectatur.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 H. 4.3. 26 H. 8.2.</note> If a perſon make a Leaſe and be deprived, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigneth, the Succeſſours ſhall avoid the Leaſe, for the Law regardeth not the cauſe of Deprivation or Reſignation, which is
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170545:41"/>the Act of the party, but the act of the Ordinary in the admiſſion of the new Incumbent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In maleficiis plerumque ſpectatur exitus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 H. 3.144. Coke. l. 2.84.</note> 
                  <hi>non vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntas.</hi> If I hurt another only with an intention to beat him, and he dieth, it is Felony. So the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Law is altered, wherein it was a Rule of Law, <hi>In maleficiis ſpectatur voluntas, &amp; non exitus,</hi> as <hi>Bracton</hi> hath it, <hi>vid.</hi> 1. <hi>E.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In omnibus fere, minori aetati ſuccurritur.</hi> In a <hi>ceſſavit</hi> againſt an infant, who hath the Tenancy by deſcent, he ſhall have his age, though it be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his own Ceſſer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he cannot tell what
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170545:42"/>arrearages to tender be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Judgement.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Impoſſibile eſt unum cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus in duobus locis eſſe ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mul.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pop. Rep. 58.</note> As if a man make a leaſe of two Barns, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Rent, and for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault of payment a re-en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. If the Tenant be at one of the Barns to pay the Rent, and the Leſſor at the other to demand the Rent, and there is no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy there to pay it, yet the Leſſor cannot enter for the condition broken; becauſe there was no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault of the Tenant, he being at one Barn; for it is not poſſible for him to be in two places toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In praeſentia majoris,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ployd. 498. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſat potentia minoris.</hi> Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriations
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170545:42"/>made by the Pope, Patron, and King, were good before <hi>Stat.</hi> 25. <hi>H.</hi> 8. without the Biſhop; becauſe in the power of the greater, the leſſer ceaſeth, the Pope being ſupreme Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In quo quis deliquit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke Litt. 233. <hi>b.</hi> Groke Rep. fol. 183. Litt. 233. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>in eo de jure puniendus eſt.</hi> If the Keeper of the Park pull down the Lodge or any Houſe within the Park, for putting of Hay into it, for feeding of the Deer, or ſuch like; it is a Forfeiture, and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why the Office is forfeited, is, that he may be puniſhed in that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he offended.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In omnibus obligationi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus quibns dies non ponitur,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">20 E. 4.8. 21 E. 4.8.</note>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:170545:43"/>
                  <hi>praeſenti die debetur. Et nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la temporis d ſignatio prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſens denotat.</hi> When one is bound in Twenty Pounds, to pay Ten Pound, and no day of payment is limited, the leſſer ſum is due preſently to be rendred.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Judicis eſt judicare ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum allegata &amp; proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dy. fol. 12. pl. 50. Ployd. 83.6, 7. H. 4.31.</note> In a <hi>Formedon,</hi> if the demandant count upon a Foeffment in Fee; and not in Taile, if the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant demurre upon it, the Court cannot main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Declaration to be true, becauſe the Judge is to judge accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to what is alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Judicium pro veritate ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitur.</hi> And therefore,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170545:43"/>common recoveries ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered by the Tenant in Fee of the Lands of his Leſſee for Life, could not bee avoided or ſatisfied till the <hi>Stat.</hi> 14. <hi>Eliz.</hi> c. 8. And in Attaint, the firſt Judgment is ſo favoured, that the Plaintiffe ſhall have no other evidence but what he had at the firſt Triall; but the Juty, as many as they will, to confirm the firſt Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Judicium à non ſuo ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice datum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 10.76. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>nullius eſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti.</hi> As if the Sheriff, who is prohibited by the Law to hold his Turn within a Moneth after <hi>Michaelmas,</hi> holdeth his Turn after the Moneth, and take an Indictment of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170545:44"/>Robbery at that Turn, and the Indictment is removed by <hi>Certiorari</hi> into the Kings Bench; by advice of all the Juſtices, the party was diſcharged, becauſe not within the time limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Junior non poteſt dotem promereri,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke Litt. 33. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>nec obſtavit mulieri, minor atas viri.</hi> If the Woman be not of the age of nine years, ſhe ſhall not have Dower: but if ſhe be of that age, it mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not what age the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band be of, though but four or five.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jura naturalia ſunt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutabilia.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 7.15. <hi>b.</hi> Bracton, l. 9. c. 23.33 H. 6.55.</note> As if a man have a Ward by reaſon of a Seigniory, and is out-lawed, he forfeiteth his Wardſhip to the King:
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170545:44"/>but if he have the Ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of his Son or Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which is heir appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, and is out-lawed, he doth not forfeit this Wardſhip; for Nature hath annexed it to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Father.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ipſae etenim leges cupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt ut jure regantur.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lit. Com. 10. <hi>a.</hi> 271. <hi>a.</hi> Coke l. 5.100.</note> If partition be made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ween partners of Land in Fee ſimple, and for owelty of partition, one granteth a Rent to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther generally, the gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee ſhall have a Fee ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple without the word [heirs] becauſ the grantor hath a Fee ſimple, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration whereof he granteth the Rent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jura publica anteferenda privatis; &amp;,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 130. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>jura publica
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170545:45"/>ex privatis promiſcue deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di non debent</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in protection either for being in the Kings ſervice,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mirror.</hi> c. 3. Sect. <hi>Britton.</hi> 281.</note> as the Kings Souldier, or of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell as the Kings Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour, <hi>pro negotiis regni,</hi> both theſe things for the publick good of the realm private mens actions, and ſuit muſt be ſuſpended for a convenient time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jus accreſcendi praefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur oneribus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. com. 185. <hi>a.</hi> 453.3.13.</note> As if one joynt-tenant grant a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon paſture, or of Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bary, Eſtovers, or Corody &amp;c. out of his part; or a way over the Land; this ſhall not bind the ſurvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jas accreſcendi praefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ultimae voluntati</hi> If<note place="margin">Litt. Com. 185. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:170545:45"/>two joyn-tenants be of Land in fee ſimple, and one of them deviſeth that which to him belongeth by his teſtament, and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, this deviſe is void, becauſe the Survivour claimeth by the firſt Feof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jus deſcendit &amp; non ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. com. 345. <hi>a. b.</hi>
                  </note> As when an eſtate is turned to a right by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeizin, diſcontinuance, &amp;c. but in caſe of a title, the Land deſcends.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Juſtum non eſt aliquem ante matrimonium natum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke. l. 8.101.14 E. 2. baſtard. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>mortuum, facere baſtardum qui toto tempore ſuo pro le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitimo habebatur.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Doc. &amp; Stud.</note> If baſtard Eigne after the fathers death enter into the land and occupy it during his life without interruption
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170545:46"/>of the mulier puiſne, and dye ſeized, the mulier is barred for ever.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>L.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lex eſt ſumma ratio.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 97. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> The common Law is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but Reaſon; which is to be underſtood of an artificial perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of reaſon gotten by long ſtudy, obſervation, and experience, and not of every mans naturall reaſon, for <hi>nemo naſcitur artifex.</hi> This legall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is <hi>ratio ſumma.</hi> And therefore if all the reaſon that is diſperſed into ſo many ſeverall heads were united into one, yet could he not make ſuch a law as the Law of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170545:46"/>is; becauſe, by ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of many ages, it hath been refined by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite number of grave and learned men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Licet Tenenti vetus opus reficere,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">44 E. 3.21 44.11. H. 4.32.</note> 
                  <hi>non novum facere.</hi> A Tenant may cut down Trees for the amend ment of houſes, or reparation of them. But if the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of a new houſe comes in Queſtion, as to build a Stable; or, if no houſe be built upon the Land at the time of the leaſe, the Leſſee may not cut down Trees; to make a houſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Loquendum ut vulgus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 4.46. <hi>a.</hi> Ployd. 169. Coke l. 4.64. <hi>b.</hi> l. 7.11.</note> Words ſhall be taken ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the vulgar and ordinary conſtruction as though a perſon attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170545:47"/>be a perſon convict and more. And therefore it is the office of Judges to take and expound the words, which the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people uſe to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe their intent by, according to their intent, and not according to the true definition.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lex non praecipit inutilia.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 126.127.79, <hi>a.</hi> 197. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> A villain ſhall not by the Law have any appeal a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Lord, for in appeal of Mayhem a man ſhall recover but his dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages; and if the Villain in that caſe recover dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages againſt his Lord, and from the villain, and ſo the recovery void.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:170545:47"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lex ſemper intend't quod convenit rationi.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. com. 78. <hi>b.</hi> 182. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> The Guardian in Chivalry ſhall have the cuſtody of the heir, and his land untill become to his full age of one and twenty years: becauſe, by intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Law the heir is not able to do Knights ſervice before that age, which is grounded upon apparant reaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lex ſpectat natura or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. com. 92 <hi>a</hi> 97. Ployd. 540.</note> If tenant in ſocage hold of the Lord by Feal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and a roſe, the Lord ſhall have for his reliefe a Roſe, &amp;c. or other flowers: the tenant dyeth in winter, the Lord can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſtrain for his relief, untill the time that roſes by courſe of the year
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170545:48"/>may have their growth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lex non cogit ad im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibilia.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 231. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> If a deed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in one Court, it may be pleaded in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Court without ſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lex libertati dat favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 124. <hi>b.</hi> 139. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> If a villain ſue an action of treſpaſs or any other action againſt his Lord, in one County; and the Lord ſaith, that he ſhall not be anſwered: becauſe, he is his villain regardant to his Mannor in another County; and the Plantiff ſaith, that he is free, and of a free eſtate, and not a villain, this ſhall be tryed in the County where the Plantiff hath conceived his action; and not in the County
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170545:48"/>where the Mannor is, and this is in favour of Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lex citiùs tolerare vult privatum damnum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 152. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>quàm publicum malum.</hi> If there be Lord, Meſne, and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; and the Tenant holdeth of the Meſne by ſervice of five ſhillings; and the Meſne holdeth over by ſervice of twelve pence: If the Lord <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramont</hi> purchaſe the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancie, in ſee, then the ſervice of the meſnalty is extinct, becauſe when the Lord <hi>Paramont</hi> hath the Tenancy, he holdeth of his Lord next <hi>Paramont</hi> to him; and if he ſhould hold this of him which was Meſne, then he ſhould hold the ſame
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170545:49"/>tenancy immediately of divers Lords, by divers ſervices, which ſhould be inconvenient; and the Law will ſooner ſuffer a miſchief, then an incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience, and therefore the Signiory of the meſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty is extinct.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Liberata pecunia non liberat offerentem.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. com. 207. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> If an obligation of one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds be made with condition for the payment of fifty pounds at a day, the Obligor tenders the mony, and the obligee refuſeth the ſame: yet in action of debt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Obligation, if the Defendant plead the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and refuſal, he muſt alſo plead that he is yet ready to pay the money,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170545:49"/>tender the ſame in Court.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Line a recta ſemper prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fertur tranſverſali.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. com. 10. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> For deſcents, it is a Maxime in Law, Lineal deſcent which is conveyed down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in a right line, (as from the Grandfather to the Father, from the Father to the Son,) ſhall inherit before the heire by collaterall deſcent, which is derived from the ſide of the lineall as Grandfathers brother, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>M.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mala Grammatica non vitiat chartam.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. 146. <hi>b.</hi> Coke. l. 9. 48.4 H. 6.16</note> As <hi>Nec aliquid in eo ſpecificatum non aliter ſe extendat, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:170545:50"/>Here is a double nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, <hi>Nec &amp; non,</hi> which in Grammatical conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on amounteth to an affirmative; for <hi>Negatio deſtruit negationem &amp; am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo faciunt affirmativum;</hi> yet the Law that princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally reſpecteth ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, doth judge the proviſo to be a negative, according to the intent of the parties, and not according to the Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical conſtruction, to the end the proviſo may take effect.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Maritus &amp; uxor animae duae ſunt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 6. <hi>b.</hi> 41. <hi>a.</hi> 112. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>in una carne.</hi> Therefore a Wife cannot be produced either a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt or for her husband; for it might be a cauſe of implacable diſcord, and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170545:50"/>diſſention, betwixt the Husband and Wife, and a mean of great inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Malus uſus abolendus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 141. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> If a man will preſume that if any Cattel were upon the demeans of the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor there doing damage, that the Lord of the Mannor for the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hath uſed to diſtrain them, and the diſtreſs to retain till fine were made to him for the damages at his will; this preſcription is void, becauſe it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt reaſon. And the rule is, <hi>In conſuetudinibus non diuturnitas temporis, ſed ſoliditas rationis eſt conſideranda.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Maxime paeci contraria ſunt vis &amp; injuria.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 161. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> And
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170545:51"/>therefore <hi>Britton</hi> ſaith well, ſpeaking in the perſon of the King. <hi>Nous volous quae touts gents pluis uſeant judgment quae for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce.</hi> And therefore is it,<note place="margin">Ib. 254. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> that in Rent-ſervice, Charge and Seck; Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtallment, (which is an incountring or menacing the Lord in the way, that he dare not come on the Land to diſtraine, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the rent,) is a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeizin. And in ſuch caſe claim of the Land ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void a diſcent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meliorem conditionem facere poteſt minor,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ib. 337. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>deterio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom nequaquem.</hi> If the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant make a feoffment; he may enter either with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in age, or at full age: like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe after his death his
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170545:51"/>heir may enter:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Minor jurare non poteſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 172. <hi>b.</hi> Bracton. 5. l. fol. 340. <hi>b.</hi> 46 E. 3.10.9.3.424.</note> And therefore he cannot be of an Inqueſt. An In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant cannot make his Law of <hi>Non ſummons;</hi> therefore the default ſhall not prejudice him. An In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant cannot upon his oath, make his Law in action of debt. 26. E. 3.63. <hi>Dy.</hi> 7.104. 11 <hi>H.</hi> 6.40. 1. <hi>H.</hi> 7.15.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Modus &amp; Conventio vinciunt legem.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. com. 41. <hi>b.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 166. <hi>a.</hi> Bracton. l. 4. fol. 222. 21 H. 6.46: 10 B. 4.13.</note> To every Tenant for life, the Law, as incident to his Eſtate, without proviſion of the party, giveth him three kinds of Eſtovers; that is, Houſebote, which is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, viz. <hi>Eſtoverium aedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficandi, &amp; ardendi.</hi> Ploughbote, that is, <hi>Esto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verium
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170545:52"/>arandi.</hi> And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Haybote, which is, <hi>Eſtoverium claudendi.</hi> And theſe Eſtovers muſt be reaſonable. And theſe the Leſſee may take upon the Land demiſed, without any aſſignment; unleſſe he be reſtrained by ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Govenant: for an Agreement doth alter the Law.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mulieres ad probatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem status hominis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lit. Com. 6. <hi>b.</hi> Fleta. l. 2. c. 44.23. E. 1. Villaine 36, 37. 29 E. 1. Ib. 32. Lit. Com. 142. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>admitti non debent.</hi> And therefore are women, by Law, wholly excluded, to prove a man to be a vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Multa tranſeunt cum univerſalitate, quae per ſe non tranſeunt.</hi> If a man hath a Rent-ſeck of the part of his mother, and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170545:52"/>the Tenant of the Land grant a Diſtreſſe to him and his Heirs, and the Grantee dieth; the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe ſhall go with the Rent to the heir of the part of the mother, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident and appurtenant to the Rent; for now is the Rent-ſeck become a Rent-charge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>N</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Negationi nihil impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">11 H. 7.23. 21 H. 6.41. 10. E. 3.10.</note> If a Tenant wage his Law of <hi>non ſum;</hi> this doth not imply that he was Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nemo debet bis puniri pro uno delicto.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 4. fol. 43. <hi>Hudſon's</hi> caſe.</note> In Appeal of <hi>Mayhem,</hi> the Defendant pleaded that before, &amp;c. and the Plaintiff recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170545:53"/>in Treſpaſſe, for the ſame Ba ery and Woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, 200 <abbr>l.</abbr> and ſatisſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction acknowledged; and the Barre was adjudged good.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 309. <hi>b.</hi> Coke. l. 5. fol. III. <hi>Mallarids</hi> caſe. Peck. 15. Ployd. 432. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Nemo poteſt plus juris in alium transſerre quam ipſe habet.</hi> If the Conuſee of a Fine, before any At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tournment by Deed In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dented and Inrolled, bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaineth and ſelleth the Signiory to another; the Bargainee ſhall not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain, becauſe the Bargai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor could not diſtrain.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Neminem oportet eſſe ſapientiorem legibus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 97. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> The Law is the perfection of Reaſon. And if all the Reaſon that is diſperſed into ſo many ſeverall Heads, were united into
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170545:53"/>one, yet could hee not make ſuch a Law as the Law of <hi>England</hi> is; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by ſo many ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Ages, it hath been refined by an infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of grave and learned men; ſo that it is <hi>ratio ſumma.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 162. <hi>a.</hi> 49 E. 3.14.49. Aſſ. 5.29. Aſſ. 49.</note>
                  <hi>Neme tenetur expone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſe infortuniis &amp; pericu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis:</hi> And therefore fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalment, with a menace of life and members, is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſſeizin of rent-ſervice, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arge, and ſeck.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Liet: com. 145. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Nemo punitur pro alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> delicto.</hi> A man cannot claime propriety by his Bailiff or Sarjeant, in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plevin; and the reaſon is, for that if the claime fall out to be falſe, hee ſhall be fined for his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt;
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170545:54"/>which the Lord cannot be, [unleſſe he make claim himſelfe; for he ſhall not be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for his Bailiff's of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ployd. 32. <hi>b.</hi> 39 H. 6.22.</note>
                  <hi>Nem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tenetup prodere ſeipſum.</hi> As if a man grant to one an Annuity, <hi>pro conſilie impendende,</hi> the Grantee ſhall have a Writ of Annuity, without ſhewing, that he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him counſell; for the ſhewing of it is not for his benefit; and denial of counſell goeth in defei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance of the Annuity: which ought to be ſhewn by the Defendant, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe for his benefit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nihil quod eſt inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niens vel contra rationem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lit. Com. 97. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>eſt licitum.</hi> Tenant in
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170545:54"/>Frank marriage, ſhall do fealty to his Lord, before the fourth degree, be paſt; for it ſhould be incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, and againſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that a man ſhall be Tenant of an eſtate of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance to another, and the Lord ſhould not have any manner of ſervice; for, if he does not fealty, hee ſhall not do any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſervices to his Lord:</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 188. <hi>a</hi> Ployd. 419. <hi>Brace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge</hi>'s caſe</note>
                  <hi>Nihil de re accreſcit ei, qui nihil in re quando jus accreſceret habet.</hi> If two joynt Tenants be of a Rent, and one of them diſſeize the Tenant of the Land; this is a ſeverance of the Joynture for a time, for the moity of the Rent is ſuſpended by
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170545:55"/>unity of poſſeſſion, and therefore cannot ſtand in Joynture with the other moiety in poſſeſſion. And here, if one of them die, there ſhall be no ſurvi, vour. For there ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be any ſurvivour, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the thing be in joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture at the inſtant of the death of him that firſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Non refert an quis aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſum praebeat verbis au rebus &amp; factis.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">44 E. 3. <hi>fines.</hi> 37.37 H. 6.17. 7. <hi>E.</hi> 3.50.</note> If the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron accept the grant of a Reverſion, that amoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to an Attornment. 44. <hi>E.</hi> 3.37. Hee which hath <hi>intereſſe termini,</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, by expreſs words, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render it, but the accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of a new Leaſe ſhall drown it.</p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:170545:55"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Non valet impedimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum quod de jure non ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur effectum;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 4.31. <hi>Frenches</hi> eaſe. Litt. 361. <hi>h.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp;, Quod contralegem ſit, pro infecto habotur.</hi> If Copy-hold Lands be forfeited, or eſcheat, and the Lord Leaſe them for years or life, or any other eſtate by Deed, or without Deed; this Land can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver again be granted by Copy, for the Cuſtom is deſtroyed. For, during theſe Eſtates, the Land was not demiſable by Copy. But if the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption be tortious, as by Diſſeizin and Diſcent, falſe Verdict, or errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judgement; there it may be granted again by Copy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Non afficit conatus, niſi</hi>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:170545:56"/>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 6.4 <hi>Mildmay</hi>'s caſe.</note> 
                  <hi>ſequatur effectus.</hi> A gift in tail upon condition, that his Eſtate ſhall ceaſe, if he go about to alien, &amp;c. This condition is void; for endeavour of a breach is not a breach.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Non eſt baeres viventis.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 22. <hi>b.</hi> 217. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> If a man, by Deed, make a Leaſe for years, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder to the right heirs of <hi>J. S.</hi> and the Leſſor make livery to the Leſſee, <hi>ſecundum formam Chartae;</hi> this Livery is void, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe during the life of <hi>J. S.</hi> his right heir can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not take; and in that caſe the Free-hold ſhall not remain in the Leſſor, and expect the death of <hi>J. S.</hi> during the term. For, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit <hi>J. S.</hi> dye during the term, yet the remainder is
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170545:56"/>void, becauſe a Livery of ſeizin cannot expect.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Non valet pactum de re meanon alienanda.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 223. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> As a Feofment upon condition, that the Feoffee ſhall not alien, the condition is void.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nullum iniquum in jure praeſumendum.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 4. fol. 70. <hi>Hynde</hi>'s caſe.</note> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords are ſo high and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred, that they import in themſelves inviolable ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which if any gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay, they ſhall be tryed only by themſelves, and not by the Country. And if averment againſt a Record ſhould be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, then the effect and validity of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord ſhould be tryed by the Country, which is againſt the Rule of Law, <hi>Nullum iniquum eſt in ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170545:57"/>praeſumendum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nullum tempus occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit Regi.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 118. <hi>a.</hi> 90. <hi>b.</hi> 119. <hi>a.</hi> Ployd. 156.159. 9 H. 6.21.12 H. 7.12</note> 
                  <hi>For, if the villain of the King purchaſe any lands, and alien, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King (upon and office found for him) doth enter; yet the King, after Office found, ſhall have the Land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nullum ſemile eſt idem.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 43. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> Tenant by Statute Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, Staple, or Elegit; are ſaid to hold land, <hi>ut liberum tenementum,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till their debt be paid: Yet in truth they have not Freehold, but a Chattle, which ſhall go to the Executors; and the Executors, if ouſted, ſhall have an Aſſize. But is <hi>ſimilitudinaric;</hi> becauſe they ſhall by the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170545:57"/>have an Aſſize, as a Tenant of the Freehold ſhall have; and in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect hath ſimilitude of a Freehold; but, no like is the ſame thing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nullus commodum capere potest de injuria ſua propria.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 148. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> If <hi>B.</hi> make a Leaſe of one Acre for life to <hi>A.</hi> and <hi>A.</hi> is ſeized of another Acre in Fee; and <hi>A.</hi> granteth a rent-charge to <hi>B.</hi> out of both Acres, and doth waſte in that Acre which he holdeth for life, <hi>B.</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covereth in waſte. The whole Rent is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct, but ſhall be appor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned; and yet <hi>B.</hi> claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth one Acre under <hi>A:</hi> So if <hi>A.</hi> had aliened in Fee, and <hi>B.</hi> had entred for the forfeiture.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:170545:58"/>
               <head>O.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oninis privatio praeſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponit habitum.</hi> A perſon maketh the Leaſe for years, reſerving a Rent, and dieth; the Leaſe is determined by his death. Alſo in a reall action, a Parſon, Vicar, Archdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, Prebend, ſhall have did of the Patron and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, as Tenant for life ſhall have. So that to many purpoſes, a perſon hath in effect but an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate for life, and to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a qualified Fee ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. But the entire Fee and Right is not in him, and therefore he cannot diſcontinue the Fee ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that he hath not, nor
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170545:58"/>ever had; for, <hi>Omnis privatio praeſupponit habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Omnia quae movent ad mortem, ſunt deodanda.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 5.190. <hi>Fox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi>'s caſe. Stamf. l. 1. c. 12. fol. 20</note> If a man ride in a Chariot, and the Chariot fall upon him and kill him, the Horſes, as well as the Chariot, ſhall be a Deo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dand.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Omne teſtamentum mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te conſummatum eſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 4. fol. 60. <hi>Forſe</hi> and <hi>Hemblings</hi> caſe. Lit. 112. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> The making of a Will is but an inception thereof, and it doth not take any ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect till the death of the Deviſor.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Omne majus continet in ſe minus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 5. 114. <hi>Wade</hi>'s caſe.</note> If a man be bound in a Bond for a ſum of money, to be paid at a certain day; and at the day, the Obligee ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170545:59"/>more than the ſumme; yet it is a good tender, for the reaſon above-ſaid.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 43. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Omne majus trahit ad ſe minus.</hi> The King cannot be ſaid to be a <hi>Minor;</hi> for when the Royall Body Politick of the King doth meet with the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall capacity in one perſon, the whole Body ſhall have the quality of the Body politick, which is the greater, and more worthy, and wherein is no minority.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Omnia quae ſunt uxoris, ſunt ipſius viri.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 112. <hi>a. b.</hi>
                  </note> And therefore ſhe is diſabled to contract with any; without the conſent of the husband; neither hath ſhe power to diſpoſe of any perſonal eſtate in her own right.</p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:170545:59"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Omnis ratihabitio retro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trahitur,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 180. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp; mandato ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiparatur.</hi> As if <hi>A.</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeize one to the uſe of <hi>B.</hi> who knoweth not of it, and <hi>B.</hi> aſſent to it; in this caſe, till the agreement, <hi>A.</hi> was Tenant to the Land; and after agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>B.</hi> is Tenant of the Land; but both be diſſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zors.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 5. fol. 321. <hi>Playters</hi> caſe.</note>
                  <hi>Oportet ut res ceria de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducatur in judicium. Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> brought an action of Treſpaſſe againſt one <hi>W. Wuare clauſum ſuum fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git, &amp; piſces ſuos cepit;</hi> without ſhewing the number or nature of the fiſhes; and it was reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that the Count ſhould have compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended the fiſhes in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170545:60"/>that the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant might have a certain anſwer; and upon which, a certain Judgement might be given.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>P.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pater eſt quem nuprie demonſtrant.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 123. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> And therefore if a Villain have a Baſtard by a woman, and marrieth her, the Biſtard is no Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain, becauſe the Villain cannot be ſaid to be his father, he being a Baſtard.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pendente lite nihil inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetur.</hi> At the Common Law,<note place="margin">Litt. Com. 344. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> if hanging the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re impedit</hi> againſt the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, for refuſing of his Clerk, and before the Church were full, the Patron brought a <hi>Quare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>impedis</hi>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:170545:60"/>againſt the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, and hanging the Suit, the Biſhop admit and inſtitute a Clerk, at the preſentation of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other: In this caſe, if Judgement be given for the Patron againſt the Biſhop, the Patron ſhall have a Writ to the Biſhop, to remove the Incumbent, that came in, <hi>pendente lite,</hi> by uſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But ſince <hi>Weſtm.</hi> 2. among other things, it is enquired, <hi>Ex officie,</hi> if the Church be full, and of whoſe preſentation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Perſpicue vera non ſunt probanda.</hi> The Lord <hi>Cook,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 16. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> in his Commentary up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Littleton,</hi> obſerves, that Mr. <hi>Littleton</hi> never citeth any Authority through
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170545:61"/>his whole Book, but when the caſe is rare, or may ſeem doubtfull; which appeareth in this, that he putteth no caſe, but hath warrant of good authority in Law. The like of Juſtice <hi>Fitzherbert</hi> in his <hi>Natura Brevium,</hi> that he never citeth autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, but when the caſe is rare or doubtful.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plus precat author,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">13 H. 7.10. <hi>Stamf.</hi> l. 1. c. 45.21 E. 4.71.</note> 
                  <hi>quam actor.</hi> If one be preſent at the death of a man, and incite another to ſtrike and kill him, by this he is principal, as well as he that killed him.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 14.6.</note>
                  <hi>Poſſeſſio fratris de foede ſimplici, facit ſororem eſſe haeredem.</hi> A man ſeized of lands in Fee-ſimple, hath iſſue a ſon and a daughter
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170545:61"/>by one venter, and a ſon by another venter, and dieth; and the eldeſt ſon enters, and dies without iſſue; the daughter ſhall have the land, and not the youngeſtion. The like of an Uſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ib. 10. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Propinquior exeludit propinquum, &amp; propinquus remotum, &amp; remotus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motiorem.</hi> And therefore the Fathers brother, and his poſterity, ſhall inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit before the grandfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers brother, and his poſterity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Proximus ſum egomet mihi.</hi> And therefore in Legacies, it is reaſon, that the Executors ſhall have preferment of ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before others; and the Law maketh allowance
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170545:62"/>to them before any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Q.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quando lex aliquid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedit, concedere videtur &amp; id,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 55. <hi>a.</hi> 153. <hi>a.</hi> Coke Rep. <hi>Lyford</hi>'s caſe.</note> 
                  <hi>ſine quo res eſſe non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt.</hi> If Leſſee at will ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the land, and the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, after it is ſown, and before the corn is ripe, put him out; yet the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee ſhall have the corn, and ſhall have free entry, egreſſe and regreſſe, to cut and carry away the corn.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quando aliquid fieri prohibetur ex directo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. <hi>p.</hi> 23. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibetur &amp; per obliquum.</hi> A Feoſment upon condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the Feoffee ſhall not alien to ſuch a
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170545:62"/>one, naming his name, is good. And in this caſe, if the Feoffee infeoff <hi>J. N.</hi> of intent and purpoſe, that he ſhall infeoffe <hi>J. S.</hi> ſome hold this a breach of the condition.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quando jus Domini Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis &amp; ſubditi concurrunt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 77. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>jus Regis praeferri debet.</hi> If a man hold lands of the King by Knight-ſervice, <hi>in Capite;</hi> and other lands of other Lords, and dieth, his Heir within age; the King ſhall have the Wardſhip of all the lands, by his prerogative.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quaelibet haereditas na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turaliter ad haeredes haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditabiliter deſcendit;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 11. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam naturaliter aſcendit, niſi a latere.</hi> If there be father, uncle, and ſonne;
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170545:63"/>and the ſon purchaſe land in fee-ſimple, and die without iſſue, living his father; his uncle ſhall have the Land, as heir to the ſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quae in partes dividi ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queunt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">14 E. 3. Fitz. 1. <hi>Kitchin.</hi> fol. 134. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſolida a ſingulis praeſtentur.</hi> If my Tenant that holdeth of me by a Harriot, alien part of the land to another; every one of them ſhall pay Harriot, becauſe it is an entire thing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quaelibet conceſſio for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſime contra donatorem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretauda.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 42. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> If Tenant in Fee make a leaſe for life, without mentioning for whoſe life, it ſhall be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for the life of the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee, and ſhall be taken more ſtrongly againſt the Leſſor.</p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:170545:63"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qui non habet in aere,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hobart</hi>'s Rep. fol. 133.</note> 
                  <hi>luat in corpore.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Law hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided ſeveral executions for the executing of the Law; and he that hath not to pay of his goods, &amp;c. muſt ſuffer in his body by impriſonment:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qui ex damnato etitu naſcuntur,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 3. <hi>b.</hi> 78. <hi>a.</hi> 123. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>inter liberos non computentur.</hi> A man makes a leaſe to <hi>B.</hi> the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the eldeſt iſſue male of <hi>B.</hi> and the heirs males of his body: <hi>B.</hi> hath iſſue a baſtard ſon; he ſhall not take the remainder, becauſe in Law he is not his iſſue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qui haeret in litera, hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret in cortice.</hi> The ſtatute of <hi>Glouc.</hi> c. 5. which gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the action of waſte
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170545:64"/>againſt the Leſſee for life, or years (which lay not againſt them at Common Law) ſpeaketh of one that holdeth for term of years in the plurall num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; and yet though it be a penall Law, whereby treble dammages, and the place waſted ſhall be recovered, yet tenant for half a year being with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſame miſchief, ſhall be within the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, though out of the letter of the Law.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qui ad mit medium, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimit finem.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 161. <hi>a.</hi> 26 Aſſ. 17.3 E. 4.2.</note> And, <hi>Qui ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruit aditum, deſtruit com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum:</hi> And therefore, if a man be diſturbed to enter and manute his land, this is a diſſeizin of the land it ſelf.</p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:170545:64"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qui peccat ebrius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 247. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>luat ſobrius.</hi> A drunkard who is <hi>voluntarius daemon,</hi> hath no priviledge thereby, but what hurt or ill ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he doth, his drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe doth aggravate it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qui per alium facit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 258. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>per ſeipſum facere videtur.</hi> If the maſter command the ſervant to go to the Land, and make claim there to avoid the diſcent; if the ſervant doth all that which is command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and which his Maſter ought to do, there it is as ſufficient, as if his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter did it himſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qui ſemel Actionem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuntiavit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. Coke l. 8. f. 58. <hi>Beecher</hi>'s caſe.</note> 
                  <hi>amplius repetere non poteſt.</hi> A <hi>retraxit</hi> is a barre of all actions of like
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170545:65"/>or inferiour nature.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qui ſentit commodum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 5.99. <hi>Rook's</hi> caſe. c. l. 5.24. Dean and Chapter of <hi>Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors</hi> caſe. Hob. 4. f.</note> 
                  <hi>ſentire debet &amp; onus.</hi> The Commiſſioners in the Commiſſion of Sewers, ought to tax all which are in dammage, or in danger of dammage, and not only him which hath the lands next adjoyning to the river: for it may be that the rage and force of the water might be ſuch, that the value of the land adjoyning would not ſerve to amend it, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſtatute would have all in peril,<note place="margin">6 H. 6. c. 5.</note> and which take commodity by the making of the Banks to be contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary to the amendment thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quod ab initio non valet,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170545:65"/>tractu temporis non convae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſcet.</hi> Tenant for life of a carve of Land, the rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the father in fee, the Son and Heir appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of the Father indow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his Wife of this carve by the aſſent of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Tenant for life dyeth, the Husband dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, the reverſion was a Tenement in the father, and yet this is no good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowment, <hi>ex aſſenſu patris</hi> becauſe the father at the time of the aſſent had but a reverſion expectant upon a freehold, (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he could not have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed his own Wiſe) though the Tenant for life dyed, living the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quod prius eſt tempore,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com: 14. <hi>ae.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:170545:66"/>
                  <hi>potius eſt jure; &amp;, quod pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us dignius.</hi> And therefore among the males, the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt brother and his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity ſhall inherit lands in fee ſimple, before any younger brother, or any deſcending from him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quod ſemel meum eſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 49. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>amplius meum eſſe non poteſt.</hi> And therefore, if a man let land for a term of years, the remainder over to another for life, or in tail, or in fee; in this caſe it behoveth the Leſſor to make livery of ſeizin to the Leſſee for years, otherwiſe nothing paſſeth to them in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder, although the Leſſee enters into the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nements. And if the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170545:66"/>in this caſe enter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any livery of ſeizin made to him, then is the freehold, and alſo the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, in the leſſor. And if the Leſſor after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards make livery to the Leſſee, it is void, for by the entry of the Leſſee he is in actuall poſſeſſion, and livery cannot be made to him that is in poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quod ſemel placuit in electionibus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 146. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>amplius diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicere non poteſt.</hi> If a man grant by his deed a rent charge to another, and the rent is behind, the grantee may bring a writ of Annuity, or diſtrain at his election, but he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have both together. For if he recover by a
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170545:67"/>writ of annuity, the land is diſcharged of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs. And if he diſtrain for the arrearages, and the Tenant ſue a Replevin, and the grantee avow the taking of the diſtreſs in the land, in a Court of Record; then is the land charged, and the perſon of the Grantor diſcharged of the Action of Annui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quoties in verbis nulla eſt ambiguitas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 14.7. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ibi nulla expoſitio contra verba ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſae fienda eſt.</hi> If a rent be granted out of the Mannour of <hi>D.</hi> and the Grantor grant over, that if the rent be behind, the Grantee ſhall diſtrain for the ſame rent in the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of <hi>S.</hi> this is but a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170545:67"/>in the mannor of <hi>S.</hi> For the Law needs not to make conſtruction, that this ſhall amount to the grant of a rent, for here a rent is expreſly granted to be iſſuing out of the Mannor of <hi>D.</hi> and the parties have expreſly li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited out of what land the Rent ſhall iſſue, and upon what land the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs ſhall be taken, and the Law will not make an expoſition againſt the expreſs words and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quod conſtat clare,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 9. fol. 33. <hi>Batens</hi> caſe.</note> 
                  <hi>non debet verificari.</hi> In a <hi>Quod permittat,</hi> if it appear to the Court that the Nuſance is to the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of the Plantiff, he
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170545:68"/>need not ſhew it ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; as if the houſe of the Defendant hangeth over the Houſe of the Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiff's.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Refert à quo fiat perqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitum.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 12. <hi>a.</hi> Ployd. 47. Sir <hi>Edw. Clere</hi>'s caſe. Coke l. 5. f. 76. <hi>Paget</hi>'s caſe.</note> None ſhall inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit any lands as heir, but only the blood of the firſt purchaſor.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Remoto impedimento, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mergit actio.</hi> If tenant for life, remainder for life, the remainder in fee, make waſte in Trees, and after he in remainder for life dye, an action of waſte is maintainable by him in the remainder in fee, for the waſte done in the life of him in remainder for life, becauſe to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inheritance of him in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder in fee; and now
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170545:68"/>the impediment, which was the mean eſtate for life, is taken away.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repellitur à Sacramento infamis.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 158, <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> If a Juror be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainted or convicted of Treaſon, or Felony, or of any offence to life, or member; or in attaint for a falſe verdict, or for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, be adjudged to the Pillory, or the like; or to be branded, or ſtigma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, or to have any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther corporall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whereby he becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth infamous; theſe and the like are principal cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of challenge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Res inter alios acta alteri nocere non debet.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 152. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if a Leſſor by Covin ſuffer a common recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the Leſſee may fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſifie
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170545:69"/>it by the Stat. of 14 E. c. 1.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>S.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Senſus verborum ex cauſa dicendi accipiendus eſt;<note place="margin">Coke l. 4. 105. <hi>Birchlye</hi>'s caſe.</note> &amp; ſermones ſecundum ſubjectam materiam: &amp; ſermo relatus ad perſonam intelligi debet de conditione perſonae.</hi> The Defendant ſaid to <hi>B.</hi> Clerk of the Kings Bench, (and ſworn to deal duly without cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption,) You are well known to be a corrupt man, and to deal corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, adjudged that the action lyes, becauſe the words <hi>ex cauſa dicendi</hi> imply, that he hath dealt corruptly in his profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:170545:69"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Semper praeſumitur,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lit. 126. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>pro legitimatione puerorum</hi> And therefore if the Husband be within the four Seas, that is within the Jurisdiction of the King of <hi>England,</hi> if the Wife hath iſſue, no proof is admitted to prove the child a baſtard.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Si mul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er nebilis nup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerit ignobili,<note place="margin">Litt. 16. <hi>b.</hi> Coke. l. 6 53. l. 4.18. <hi>b.</hi>
                     </note> deſinit eſſe nobilis.</hi> If a woman gain Nobility by Marriage, if ſhe marry under the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Nobility, ſhe lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it; otherwiſe, if No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by deſcent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Solus Deus facere poteſt haeredem.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. com. 7. <hi>b,</hi> 22. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> And therefore during the life of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he cannot be heire, but heir apparent? And therefore a Leaſe for life,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170545:70"/>the remainder to the right Heirs of <hi>J. S.</hi> if Tenant for life die, living <hi>J. S.</hi> the remainder cannot reſt, there being no heirs of <hi>J. S.</hi> but onely appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Stabitur praeſumptioni, donec probetur in contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lit. Com. 310. <hi>b.</hi> 393. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> If a man plead the Feoffment of a Mannor; he need not plead an Atturnment of the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, for that ſhall be preſumed, till it bee ſhewn to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>T.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Testamento cum duo inter ſe pugnantia reperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untur,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 112. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ultimum ratum eſt.</hi> In one Will where there
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170545:70"/>be diverſe deviſes of one thing, the laſt deviſe taketh place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Traditio loqui facit char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam.</hi> A Leaſe dated 26. <hi>May.</hi> 25,<note place="margin">Coke l. 5. f. 1. <hi>Clay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi>'s caſe.</note> 
                  <hi>Eliz.</hi> to hold from three years hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth, it was delivered at three of the Clock in the afternnon of the 20th of <hi>Junt</hi> after, from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth ſhall be taken the day of the delivery <hi>inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive,</hi> for the day of the delivery is parcel of the term; but <hi>à die confectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> or <hi>à die datus,</hi> the term beginneth the day after the date.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vana eſt potentia quae nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam venit in actum.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 2. fol. 50.</note> Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170545:71"/>in Tail,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cholmley</hi>'s caſe.</note> the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in Tail, the remainder bargains and ſells the land, and all his eſtate, to <hi>I. S.</hi> for the life of Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in Tail, the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the Queen; the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder to the Queen is void, becauſe the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee, for life of Tenant in Tail, took nothing; for it is a void Grant. And a remainder, <hi>dicitur, quaſi terra remauens,</hi> which cannot be here. And the remainder muſt take effect when the particular eſtate ends; and here it never begins. <hi>Et vana est illa potentia, quae nunquam venit in actum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi factum nullum ibi fortia nulla,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 4. fol. 43. <hi>Syers</hi> caſe.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; ubi non eſt principalis non potest eſſe
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170545:71"/>acceſſarius.</hi> If the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall be pardoned, or hath his Clergy, the Acceſſary cannot be arraigned, for none can bee principall before it be ſo adjudged by Law; <hi>viz.</hi> by Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the Verdict or Confeſſion, or by Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary. And it ſufficeth not, that in truth he be princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall, and the acceptance of pardon, or prayer of Clergy is an argument, but no judgment in Law, that he is guilty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi eadem ratio ibi idom jus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 232. <hi>a.</hi> 191. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> If two men do a treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs to another, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſes to one of them, by his Deed, all actions per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall; and notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, ſueth an action of Treſpaſſe againſt the, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170545:72"/>the Defendant may ſhew, that the Treſpaſſe was done by him, and by another his fellow; and that the Plantiff, by his Deed, which he ſheweth forth, releaſe to his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low all actions perſonal, and demand the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And yet ſuch Deed belongeth to his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and not to him. But becauſe he may have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage by the Deed, if he will ſhew the Deed to the Court, he may plead this. By the ſame reaſon may the Feoffer, if he is come by the Deed Poll, when he ought to have advantage by the Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, compriſed within the Deed Poll.<note place="margin">Lit. Com. 32. <hi>c.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi nullum matrime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170545:72"/>ibi nulla dos.</hi> To the having of Dower it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, that the Marriage do continue; for, if that be diſſolved, the Dower ceaſeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verba accipienda ſunt in mitiori ſenſu</hi> As,<note place="margin">Coke l. 4.13.</note> Thou art a Thief, and haſt ſtollen a Tree, (ſpoken of another) it ſhall be intended a Tree ſtanding.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verba accipienda ſunt cum effectu.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cok. Rep. l. 4. f. 48. <hi>Ognel</hi>'s caſe. Litt. Com. 183. <hi>b.</hi> 112. <hi>b.</hi> Coke l. 3.23. Ployd, 197. <hi>b.</hi> 213. <hi>c.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> If Lands be given to two men, and to the heirs of their two bodies begotten; the Donees have a joynt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate for the tearm of their lives, and yet they have ſeverall inheritan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, inaſmuch as they cannot have an heir be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them ingendred; the Law will, that their
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170545:73"/>eſtate be ſuch as is reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, according to the form and effect of the words of the Gift, <hi>viz.</hi> the Heirs which the one ſhall beget of his body by any of his wives; and, ſo of the other.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erba aequivoca &amp; in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bie poſita intelliguntur dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niori &amp; potentiori ſenſu,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coke l. 6. fol. 20. <hi>Gregorie's</hi> caſe.</note> 
                  <hi>ſecundum excellentiam.</hi> As if the ſpeech or writing be of <hi>I. S.</hi> generally, it ſhall be intended of the father, where the father and ſon are both of a name. So, if of two bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of one name it ſhall be intended of the eldeſt; for theſe are more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy. So, where the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5. <hi>Phil. &amp; Mar.</hi> ſpeaketh in any Court of Record, it ſhall
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170545:73"/>be intended of the four Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the King's Atturney it Attendant there.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erba relata hoc maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me operantur per referen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam ut in eſſe videantur.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 9. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> As if the father infeoff the ſon, to have and to hold, to him and his heirs; And the ſon infeoffeth the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as fully, as the father infeoffed him: By this the father hath a fee-ſimple.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erba chartarum fortius accipiuntur contra profe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentem.</hi> As, If two joynt-Tenants grant a Rent of 10 <abbr>s.</abbr> the Grantee ſhall have a Rent of 20 <abbr>s.</abbr> out of the land.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>numquodque diſſolvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur eo ligamine quo liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. 5 H. 7.33. 4 H. 7.7. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> In an Annuity, grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by preſcription, rien
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170545:74"/>arrear, is a good plea; for this preſcription is matter in fact: But in an Annuity by Deed, it is no good plea, without ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Acquittance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltima voluntas Teſtato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris perimplenda est ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum veram intentionem.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. Com. 322. <hi>a. b.</hi>
                  </note> If a man let lands deviſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to another for life, or for years, and deviſeth the Reverſion, by his Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to another, in Fee or in Tail, and dyeth; and after, the Tenant com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits waſte: He, to whom the Deviſe was made, ſhall have writ of waſte, although the Tenant ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Atturn. And the reaſon is, for that the Will of the Deviſor may be performed, according to his intent. And if the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170545:74"/>effect of this ſhould lie up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Attournment of the Tenant, then, perchance, the Tenant would never Attorn; and then the Will of the Deviſor ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be perform'd. And for this, the Deviſee may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain, &amp;c. or bring an acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Waſte without At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tournment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Voluntas teſtatoris am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulatoria eſt uſque ad mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. 112. <hi>a. b.</hi> Coke l. 4. f. 60. <hi>Forſe</hi> and <hi>Hem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi>'s caſe.</note> And therefore<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if a man, at divers times, make divers Deviſes and Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, yet the laſt Deviſe and Will made by him, ſhall ſtand, and the other are void: for the latter Will doth countermand the firſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Volenti non fit injuria.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pop. 9.</note> As if Leſſee for twenty
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170545:75"/>yeares accept another Leaſe for ten years; the firſt Leaſe is void and gone, being the accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the ſecond, is, in Law, the ſurrender of the firſt: and no wrong in the Leſſor.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tile per inutile non vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiatur.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. com. 227. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> If the Jury give a Verdict of the whole iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, and of more<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c. that which is more is ſurplu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, and ſhall not ſtay Judgment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xor non eſt ſui-juris, ſed ſub poteſtate viri.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. com. 112. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> And therefore during the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verture, ſhe is diſabled to contract with any, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the conſent of the husband.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="rules">
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:170545:75"/>
            <head>Rules and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Law.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>LAW is an Art of well ordering a civil Society.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lawes, are Native or Poſitive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Native, are thoſe Laws, which are in us of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and therefore un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable and perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe are two-fold, like thoſe two great Lights,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bracton.</hi> l. 9.23. 3 H. 6.55.</note> 
               <hi>which God hath ſet in the Firmament of our Heart, Nature and Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="114" facs="tcp:170545:76"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Lex natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae eſt ratio ſumma, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſita in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis natu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ra, quae ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet ea quae faci enda ſunt. prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betque con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traria. <hi>Cic. l. 1.</hi> de legibus.</note>
               <hi>The Law of Nature is Soveraign Reaſon, fixed in mans nature, which mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtreth common Principles of good and Evill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Law of Reaſon is, that which deduceth Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples by the diſcourſe of ſound reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The rules of Reaſon are of two ſorts; ſome taken from Forraign Learnings, both divine and humane; the reſt proper to Law it ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of the firſt ſort are the principles and ſound con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions, from forraign Learnings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt from Divinity the Doctrine of Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To ſuch Lawes of the Church as have warrant in holy Scripture,</hi>
               <note place="margin">34. H. 6.40.</note> 
               <hi>our
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170545:76"/>Law giveth credence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Sabbath day is no day for Law-dayes:<note place="margin">1 Eliz. Dy. 168. F.N.B. 17. f. 12 E. 4.8.</note> 
               <hi>Dies Dominicus non eſt ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridicus.</hi> If a <hi>Scire facias</hi> out of the <hi>Common Pl as,</hi> bears Teſte upon a <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> it is error.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of Grammar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Words in conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, muſt be referred to the next Antecedent, when the matter it ſelf doth not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Indictment againſt <hi>I. S. ſerviens I. D: de D. im com. Mid. Butcher.</hi>
               <note place="margin">9 E. 4. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 32 H. 8. Dy. 46. <hi>b<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </note> This is not good; for <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viens</hi> is no addition, and <hi>Butcher</hi> referreth to the Maſter, which is the next Antecedent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From Logick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the Maxim of Cauſes and Effects.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="116" facs="tcp:170545:77"/>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>The Cauſe ceaſing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">5 E. 4.8. <hi>b.</hi> 7 El. D. 293. <hi>b.</hi> 13 El. 401. 13 E. 4.10. <hi>b.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the Effect doth likewiſe ceaſe.</hi> The King granteth an Office to one at will, and ten pound-fee for life,<note place="margin">14 H. 7.2.</note> 
               <hi>pro officio illo.</hi> Now if the King put him from his Office, the Fee ſhall ceaſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Things are conſtrued according to that which was the cauſe of it.</hi>
               <note place="margin">21 E. 4. 68 <hi>b.</hi> 14 E. 3.14. <hi>b.</hi> 14 Aſſ. pl. 20. 3 E. 3.84.</note> One impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned, till he be content to make an obligation at an other place, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he doth ſo, being at large; yet he ſhall avoid it by dureſs of impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Things are conſtrued according to that which is the beginning thereof.</hi>
               <note place="margin">33 Aſſ. pl. 7. 10 Eliz. Dy. 266. <hi>b.</hi>
               </note> If a ſervant (departed out of his M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſter's ſervice) kill
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:170545:77"/>his Maſter, upon malice that he bare him whilſt he was his ſervant; it is petty Treaſon.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 6. <hi>And therefore a derived power cannot be greater,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Litt. 6. 28 Aſſ. pl. 4. 2 E. 4.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>than that from which it is derived.</hi> The Atturney of one that is diſſeized, cannot make claim of from the land, if the Diſſeizee himſelf durſt have gone to the land</p>
            <p n="7">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 7. <hi>Things are diſſolved as they be contracted.</hi>
               <note place="margin">19. E. 4.1. 5 H. 7.33. <hi>b.</hi> 5 <hi>H.</hi> 7.7. <hi>b.</hi>
               </note> An Obligation, or other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in writing, cannot be diſcharged by lan Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by word.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> 8. <hi>Things grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an ill and void begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, cannot have a good perfection.</hi>
               <note place="margin">10 El. Dy. 344<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> An Infant or Feme covert, make their Will, and publiſh it, and
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170545:78"/>after dying of full age or ſole; yet the Will is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worth.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> 9. <hi>He that claimeth pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramount a thing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 &amp; 3. El. Dy. 187.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver take benefit nor hurt by it.</hi> An Executor recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth and dieth inteſtate. Adminiſtration of the firſt Teſtator is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to <hi>J. S. J. S.</hi> ſhall not ſue execution upon this Recovery; for he is Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrator to the Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor Paramount the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> 10. <hi>Things are conſtrued according to the end.</hi>
               <note place="margin">19 E. 4.3. 13. E. 3. <hi>Joynder in ayd.</hi> 10. 50. Aſſ. pl. 2.</note> Vou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chee, upon a Grand <hi>cape ad valentiam,</hi> ſhall not loſe the land, though he cannot ſave his default: For the Proceſſe is onely to this end, to have him to appear.</p>
            <pb n="119" facs="tcp:170545:78"/>
            <p>
               <hi>In the Maxim of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects and Adjuncts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/>
               <hi>Where the foundation faileth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. E. 3.74. <hi>b.</hi> 49 E. 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>all goeth to the ground.</hi> A Church appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated to a ſpiritual Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration becometh diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appropriate, if the Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration be diſſolved.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/>
               <hi>Things incident cannot be ſevered.</hi>
               <note place="margin">7 E. 4.11. 12 El. 12. 381. Dy. 12 El. 12.379. 19. H. 8. Br. Inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents. 34. 3. E. 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Aſſ. 441.</note> Lord and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, by fealty and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, the Lord releaſeth his fealty; this is void: for feal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is incident to homage.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/>
               <hi>Things, by reaſon of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, are of the ſame plight.</hi> Two Copereeners make partition, and one cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants with the other to acquit the land.<note place="margin">42 E. 3. 6 E 6. Dy. 72. <hi>b.</hi> F. N. B. 21. <hi>b.</hi>
               </note> Now if the Covenantee abett his part, the Alienee ſhall have a Writ of Covenant.</p>
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:170545:79"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Perſonall things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/>
               <hi>Cannot be done by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
               <note place="margin">7 <hi>H.</hi> 4.19. 21. E. 4.34.</note> 
               <hi>Suit of</hi> Court can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be done by another.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/>
               <hi>They cannot be granted over, as matters of pleaſure eaſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">12 <hi>H.</hi> 7.25. 19 <hi>H.</hi> 8.10. 7 <hi>H.</hi> 4.36.11.3.4.1. 12 El. 179. <hi>Br.</hi> Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. 25.</note> 
               <hi>truſt, and aeuthority.</hi> A licenſe to hunt in my Parke, to go to Church over my ground, &amp;c. cannot be granted over. So a warrant of Atturney made to one to deliver ſeizin, he cannot grant this his authority over.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/>
               <hi>They dye with the perſon.</hi> When a corporal hurt or damage is done to a man,<note place="margin">2 <hi>H.</hi> 8.21.1.2. &amp; P. &amp; M. 114.</note> as to beat him, &amp;c. if he or the party beaten dye, the Action is gone.</p>
            <pb n="121" facs="tcp:170545:79"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Among the diſagreeable arguments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, from theſe that differ only is a certain reſpect and reaſon, not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and in nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Things do inure diverſty according to the diverſity of</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/>
               <hi>Time.</hi> Lands given in Frank marriage reſerving a rent,<note place="margin">26 Aſſ. pl. 66.</note> the reſervation is void<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> till the fourth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree paſt, and afterwards good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Perſon,</hi> viz.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/>
               <hi>Of the ſame perſon.</hi> One that hath a rent-charge going out of the wive's lands,<note place="margin">14. <hi>H.</hi> 8.6.</note> releaſeth it to the Husband and his. Heirs, the Husband yet ſhall not have it, but it ſhall inure to him by way of extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhment
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170545:80"/>onely, as ſeiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the right of his wife.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/>
               <hi>Severall perſons</hi> A man makes a leaſe of a Mannor except an acre,<note place="margin">1 &amp; 2 <hi>P.</hi> &amp; M. 104. 11 E. 4.2.</note> this acre is no part of the mannor as to the Leſſor, but as to him that hath right to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the Mannor by an eign title, it remaineth parcell, and therefore he ſhall make no forepriſe in his writ.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then from Relatives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/>
               <hi>No man can doe an act to himſelf.</hi>
               <note place="margin">3 El. Dy. 188. 13 <hi>H.</hi> 8.22 Lit. 147. <hi>b.</hi>
               </note> And therefore if the Sheriff ſuffer a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon recovery, it is error, becauſe he cannot ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of Compariſons from the equalls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/>
               <hi>Things are to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:170545:80"/>ſecundum equalita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem rationis.</hi> If two, four,<note place="margin">26 Aſſ. pl. 37. Coke 136. Sir <hi>Will. Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi>'s caſe. Bract. l. 1. c. 23. <hi>H.</hi> 8. Fitz.</note> or more men being ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſeized of land, joyn in a recognizance, all their lands muſt equally be extended.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From the greater and the leſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/>
               <hi>The greater doth contain the leſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">3 &amp; 4 <hi>P.</hi> &amp; M. Dy. 150. <hi>b.</hi>
               </note> By a pardon of Murder, man-ſlaughter is pardoned.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/>
               <hi>A matter of higher na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture determineth a matter of lower nature.</hi>
               <note place="margin">21 H. 7.5.33 H. 8. Dy. 50.</note> A man hath liberty by preſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and after taketh a grant of thoſe liberties by Letters Patents from the King, this determ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the preſcriptions for a matter in writing
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:170545:81"/>determineth a matter in fair.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24"/>
               <hi>The more worthy draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to it things of leſs wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">11 <hi>H.</hi> 4.31 10 El. 321 <hi>b.</hi> 3. Eliz. 238.</note> An adulterer, if he takes away another mans wife, and puts her in New cloaths, the Husband may take the wife with her cloaths.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/>
               <hi>Things acceſſary are of the nature of the Principal.</hi>
               <note place="margin">40 Aſſ. pl. 25. 7 <hi>H.</hi> 6.19. <hi>b.</hi> 26 <hi>H.</hi> 8. Dy. 7. <hi>b.</hi>
               </note> A Servant procureth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother to kill his Maſter: This is not petty Treaſon in the Servant, becauſe it is but felony in the other, which is the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="26"/>
               <hi>A Mans own words are void when the Law ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth as much.</hi>
               <note place="margin">30 Aſſ. pl. S.</note> Lands given
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:170545:81"/>to two, <hi>&amp; uni corum diu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius viventi,</hi> they make partition, and one dyeth, yet the leſſor ſhall have again the moyety of him that dyeth, for <hi>uni corum diu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ius viventi</hi> are but idle words, becauſe (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them) the joynte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant by courſe of Law is to have all if he do ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From the Rule of Method.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In things of Formali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="27"/>
               <hi>The Generals muſt go before,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Rule of the Regiſter.</note> 
               <hi>and the Specialls follow after.</hi> In a writ the general ſhall be put in demand, and in plaint, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſpeciall: as land before prede, paſture, wood, &amp;c. wood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:170545:82"/>Alders, Willows, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="28"/>
               <hi>The more worthy is to be ſet before the leſs worthy.</hi> The entire thing ſhall be demanded before the moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety,<note place="margin">ibid.</note> part,<note place="margin">ibid.</note> or parts. The thing of greater dignity before that which is of leſs: as a Meaſe before Land, a Caſtle before a meſſuage or mannor.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="29"/>
               <hi>Next are the precepts of Natural Philoſophy. Law reſpecteth the bonds of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.As the Son may main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his father, and one bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Law judgeth and eſteemeth of all according to their nature; both per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and their ages, things, actions, and the time of the doing them.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="127" facs="tcp:170545:82"/>
            <p>
               <hi>In perſons. It looketh to the excellency of ſome, and giveth them ſingular privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, and preheminencies above the reſt. As to the King, the Queen his Wife, Noble-men and Peers of the Realm: Alſo unto them of the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It tendreth the weakneſs and debilities of others,</hi> As, <hi>of men out of the Realm, or in priſon, femes Covert, (and therefore fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureth them for their Dowers,) infants, men unlettered, Ideots, &amp;c.</hi> If a diſſeizor die ſeized, the diſſeizee being all the while within age, Covert-Baron, in priſon, or out of the Realm, it ſhall be no diſcent to toll the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie of the diſſeizee. And
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:170545:83"/>an Ideot, or man of non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſane memory may enter, or have an action to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void their own Peoff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="31"/>
               <hi>It favoreth ſtrangers, not parties nor privies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Leſſee for years grants a rent-charge,<note place="margin">1 El. 198.</note> and ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet the rent ſhall be paid during the years.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore things done in anothers right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A perſon Out-lawed, or Excommunicated, may have an Action, as Executor of another man.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="32"/>
               <hi>It diſ-favoureth other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aliens, neither borne within the Realme, nor free Denizons, that they ſhall not participate of the
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:170545:83"/>Priviledges of natural-born ſubjects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eſpecially Alient that are enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alien enemies ſhall not have ſo much as a perſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al action, which other A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liens may.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Touching their Ages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="33"/>
               <hi>It holdeth</hi> 21 <hi>their full age, to make good any act they do:</hi> 14 <hi>their age of diſcretion:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That a competent age to binde a man in matter of marriage;</hi> 12 <hi>to binde the woman;</hi> 9 <hi>to deſerve her Dower.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="34"/>
               <hi>It reſpecteth every one according to worthineſs: As.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Life and liberty moſt;
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:170545:84"/>the perſon above his Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions; Freehold and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance more than it doth Chattels; Real Chattels more then Perſonal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Villain infranchiſed for an hour, is free for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. So, if infranchiſed upon condition, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is void, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>franchiſment abſolute.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="35"/>
               <hi>A matter in right, more then a matter in Poſſeſſion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">3 E. 3.88.</note> In Avowrie or Annuity, aid ſhall not be of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, if the Plaintiff be ſeized by the hands of the ſame perſon, becauſe it is of the perſon's own wrong to deny it. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, in a <hi>Ceſſavit,</hi> for that is in the right for the land.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="36"/>
               <hi>Yet it favoureth Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:170545:84"/>where the right is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall.</hi> A man purchaſeth at one time ſeveral lands,<note place="margin">8 El. 296.</note> holden of ſeverall Lords by Knights-ſervice, and dyeth: the Lord that firſt can happe the Ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of his heir, ſhall have it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It favoureth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="37"/>
               <hi>Matters of Profit and Intereſt largely; of Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi>
               <note place="margin">13 <hi>H.</hi> 7.13 12 <hi>H.</hi> 7.25.11. <hi>H.</hi> 7.12.35. <hi>H.</hi> 6.58. 4 E. 6.68. <hi>b.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Eaſe, Truſt, &amp; An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, or limitation ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> Way granted to Church over my Land, extends not to to any other but himſelf; for it is but an Eaſement. If the Sheriffe behead one that ſhould be hanged, it is felon y. A Leaſe to <hi>A</hi> and <hi>B,</hi> &amp;c. for their liv s. <hi>A</hi> dieth, <hi>B</hi> ſhall have all during
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:170545:85"/>his life, for it is an inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt. But if a Leaſe be made to <hi>J. S.</hi> during the life of <hi>A.</hi> and B. there, if one of them die, the eſtate is determined; for that is a limitation.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="38"/>
               <hi>Therefore, Theſe may be countermanded,</hi>
               <note place="margin">9 E. 4.4. <hi>b.</hi> 1 E. 5.2. 28 H. 8. Dy. 22. 14 E. 4.2. Perk. 19. <hi>b.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſo can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not thoſe.</hi> A licence to come to my houſe to ſpeak with me. Goods bailed over, to deliver to <hi>J. S.</hi> or to beſtow in almes. A Letter of At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourney to deliver ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zin. All theſe may bee countermanded, before they be dones. But if I preſent <hi>J. S.</hi> to a Church, I cannot after vary, and preſent a new; for, a kind of intereſt paſſeth out of me.</p>
            <pb n="133" facs="tcp:170545:85"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="39"/>
               <hi>It favovreth matters of Subſtance, more then mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Circumſtance.</hi> Pleas in Bar, and Replications, though the Plaintiff be afterwards Non-ſuite, make an Eſtoppell, for they are expreſs allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and material. As,<note place="margin">21 <hi>H.</hi> 7.24 <hi>b.</hi>
               </note> in Debt upon Obligaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if the.<note place="margin">33 <hi>H.</hi> 6.10. <hi>b.</hi>
               </note> Defendant plead in Barre an Acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance made at <hi>D.</hi> Or, if the Defendant plead an Acquittance, and the Plaintiff reply, That it was made by dureſs of Impriſonment at. <hi>D.</hi> Now in another action, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Defendant ſhall plead, that the Acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; nor the Plaintiff, that the dureſs was at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place. But a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:170545:86"/>in the Writ or Count, makes no Eſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel; for they are but ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">20 <hi>H.</hi> 7.11.32. <hi>H.</hi> 8. Br. <hi>Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                        <desc>••…</desc>
                     </gap>ments.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Things executed and done, more then things ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutory and to do.</hi> A Feof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the uſe of ones Will, if this Will be decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before, or at the time of hit Feoffment; it cannot be altered, becauſe it is executed.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="40"/>
               <hi>It favoureth poſſibility of things. And therefore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>H.</hi> 4.1.15. <hi>H.</hi> 7.10.41 E. 3.11.</note>
               <hi>Nothing to be void, that by poſſibility may be good.</hi> A meſſualtie is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in Tail, reſerving a Rent: this is good: for, the Tenancie may Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheat to the Doriee, and then the Donor ſhall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain for all his arrerager.</p>
            <pb n="139" facs="tcp:170545:86"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="41"/>
               <hi>It favoureth a mutual recompence.</hi> An aſſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or promiſe doth then only bind, when it is made upon good conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Actions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="42"/>
               <hi>It yieldoth favour, when for the doing of it there is neceſſity.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Br. Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor. 172.</note>
            </p>
            <p>A man, in his own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, for the neceſſity of the ſaving of his life; and a Champion, in a Writ of Right, for the neceſſity of Triall; may kill ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whither refer,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="43"/>
               <hi>Conformity, which is a kind of neceſſity.</hi> Rent muſt be demanded, though no man be upon the land to pay it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="44"/>
               <hi>Of Colour.</hi> If the heir
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:170545:87"/>indow the Anceſtors wife,<note place="margin">41 H. 3.28 22 Aſſ. pl. 64.</note> though ſhe were not dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, yet ſhe ſhall hold in Dower.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="45"/>
               <hi>It priſeth acts in Law higher, then thoſe that are done by the party.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. &amp; 3. P. M. 134. <hi>b.</hi> 29 Aſſ. pl. 23. 49. E. 3.15 2 H. 7.5.</note>For equality of partiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on among Coperceners, a Rent granted ſhall be a Fee-ſimple, without the word [heirs] and iſſuing out of the land, without ſo expreſſing it in the Grant.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="46"/>
               <hi>It reputeth, that men will alwaies deal for their own beſt advantage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="47"/>
               <hi>Believeth againſt the party, whatſoever is to his own prejudice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the time of doing things.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="137" facs="tcp:170545:87"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="48"/>
               <hi>It countenanceth more,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Things done in time of peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Litt. 97. 7 E. 3. Darren preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. 2. F. N. B. 31. <hi>b.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>than in time of war.</hi> A Diffeizin and Deſcent, in time of war, ſhall not toll the Entrie of the Daſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeized.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="49"/>
               <hi>Things done in the day, more than in the night.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A man muſt not diſtrain in the night time for Rent behinde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Where things are fit to be ſtraitned to a time, is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemeth according to the nature of the things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="50"/>
               <hi>Sometimes a whole day ſufficient.</hi> Where goods are loſt in War, and reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from the enemy by another of the Kings ſubjects, the owner ſhall have them again, if be make freſh ſuit, before
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:170545:88"/>the Sun ſet, elſe, not.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="51"/>
               <hi>Sometimes a whole year.</hi> The Lord loſeth his Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain for ever, if a Villain flie into ancient De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaſn, and there conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue a year and a day, without claim of the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="52"/>
               <hi>The third offence it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtremeth more heinous.</hi> The third Writ, not returned by the Steriff, is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, whereupon an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachment lieth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Political Precepts follow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Law ſavoureth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="53"/>
               <hi>Things for the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weal.</hi>
               <note place="margin">8 E. 4 18 <hi>b.</hi> 14 H. 8. 25.29. <hi>H.</hi> 8 Dy. 36. <hi>b.</hi>
               </note> Fiſhermen may ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtfie their comming up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the land adjoyning to the Sea, to dry their Nets; for, Fiſhing is for
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:170545:88"/>the Common-wealth, and fuſtenance of all the Realm.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publick quiet. And therefore,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="54"/>
               <hi>Common Error goeth for Law.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ploy. <hi>Manxel</hi>'s caſe. f. 2. 2 R. 3.7.</note> Whether a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Recovery be a Bar unto an Eſtate Tail, or no, is not to be diſputed; becauſe a great part of the Inheritance of the Realm doth depend upon it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of this kind are thoſe Occonomicks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Husband and the Wife are one perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">F. N. B. 78 Abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Aſſ. pl. Brook. Deniſn. 2.</note>
               <hi>The Wife is of the ſame condition with her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band; Franck, if he be free; Denizen, if he be an Engliſhman, though ſhe
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:170545:89"/>were a neiſe before, or an alien born.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="55"/>
               <hi>They cannot ſue one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r,</hi>
               <note place="margin">21 H. 7.29 <hi>b.</hi> Perk. 40.</note> 
               <hi>or make any grant unto the other, or ſuch like.</hi> If a woman marry with her Obligor, the Debt is extirect and ſhe ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have an action againſt the co obliger, if another were bound with him; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſuit againſt her husband, by enter-marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, was ſuſpended; and therefore being a perſonal action, and ſuſpended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt one, it is diſcharged againſt both.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="56"/>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon a joynt-purchaſe, during the coverture, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them taketh the whole.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Litt. 65.39 <hi>H.</hi> 6.45.21 <hi>H.</hi> 2. Judgment. 63.</note> If the husband ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en land, &amp;c. ſo given, ſhe ſhall recover the
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:170545:89"/>whole in a <hi>Cui in vita,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his death, and the Warranty of one of them, or his Anceſtors, is a bar of the whole againſt them both.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Husband is the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans head.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="57"/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="58"/>
               <hi>All ſhe hath is her hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands.</hi> If goods be given to a Feme Covert,<note place="margin">21 <hi>H.</hi> 7.29. Litt. 148.14 El. Pl. 418. &amp; 191 16 E 4.8.7 <hi>H.</hi> 6.1.39 <hi>H.</hi> 6.27.</note> and another; the Joynture is ſtrait-way ſevered, and the husband and the other are Tenants in common: and the Executors of the husband ſhall have all the goods that were his wives.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="59"/>
               <hi>Her will is become his will, and ſubject unto it.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="142" facs="tcp:170545:90"/>
            <p>If an action of Treſpaſs be brought againſt Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and Wife, and the wife come in by <hi>Cepi corpus,</hi> and the Husband doth not appear, ſhe muſt be let at large with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Mainpriſe, till her husband doth appear; but he appearing may an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer without her, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a protection caſt by the Husband ſerveth for the wiſe alſo, becauſe ſhe cannot anſwer without him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſt, come the Morall Rules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="60"/>
               <hi>The Law favoureth right.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Litt. 158.</note> When two are in a houſe, or other Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and one layes claim by one Title, the other by
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:170545:90"/>another Title, the Law ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judgeth him in poſſeſſion that hath the right to have the tenements.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="61"/>
               <hi>Suffereth things againſt the principles of Law,</hi>
               <note place="margin">F.N.B. 69 <hi>b.</hi> 4 <hi>H.</hi> 7.40.11 <hi>H.</hi> 7.10.</note> 
               <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then a man to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his remedy.</hi> The Tenant ſhall have a replevin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord that did wrongfully diſtraine, though the beaſts be come back to himſell, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he can have no a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Treſpaſſe againſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hateh wrong.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>So that</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="62"/>
               <hi>So man ſhall take benefit of his own wrong.</hi>
               <note place="margin">13 <hi>H.</hi> 7.1.31. <hi>H.</hi> 6.60.27. <hi>H.</hi> 8.11.</note> One in execution eſcapes, and the Jaylor gets him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:170545:91"/>the party if he will may have him to remain in execution for him ſtill, for the eſcape is his own wrong.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="63"/>
               <hi>Of it ſelfe projudiceth no man.</hi>
               <note place="margin">12. E. 4.8.48. E. 3.27.</note> He that miſdemean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth authority that Law giveth (as if one come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Tavern, and will not goe out in ſeaſonable time; or diſtrein for rent and kill the diſtreſs) ſhall be a wrong doer <hi>ab ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eſpecially for things that cannot be imputed to his own folly.</hi>
               <note place="margin">35 <hi>H.</hi> 6.3.38 <hi>H.</hi> 8. Br.</note> The Lord Chancedor's Servant im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaded at the common Law, clameth priviledge of the Chancery, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:170545:91"/>it be diſcuſſed, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ſhall have it or no, the Lord Chancellor dyeth: yet his priviledge is allowable ſtill, for the act of the Court to adviſe of it, ſhall not prejudice him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="64"/>
               <hi>Driveth not a man to ſhew that, which by intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he knoweth not.</hi>
               <note place="margin">10. E. 4.15. 2 Mar. 128 4 E. 6.46.</note> One bound in an Obligation to ſerve <hi>J. S.</hi> for ſeven years, <hi>in omnibus mandatis ejus licitis,</hi> ſhall plead that he did ſerve him law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, without ſhewing what ſervice or in what Commandment; for no ſervant can remember all.</p>
            <pb n="146" facs="tcp:170545:92"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore It disfavoureth Fraud and Covin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="65"/>
               <hi>If a woman hath good title of</hi> Dower,<note place="margin">18 <hi>H.</hi> S. 5.</note> and cauſe <hi>I. S.</hi> to diſſeize the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the Land, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covereth her Dower a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>I. S.</hi> yet this is no good eſtate of Dower in her, for ſhe is privy to an unlawful act, which ſhould be the means of her e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="66"/>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncertainty,</hi> whereby truth is inveigled. A man grants all his Trees and Wood upon black acre,<note place="margin">1 Mar. Dy. 91. <hi>Manxel</hi>'s caſe. 10. <hi>b.</hi>
               </note> that may reaſonably be ſpared; this is a void Grant, unleſſe it be refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a third perſon's
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:170545:92"/>judgement, what may be ſpared.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Variance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="67"/> If the Writ vary from the Obligation,<note place="margin">11 E. 4.2. 4 Aſſ. pl. 2. 32 <hi>H.</hi> 6.3. 7 <hi>H.</hi> 6.22.</note> or other ſpeciality, in name, ſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name, or ſuch like in an action of debt and annui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty brought upon it, or the Count vary from the Writ; As in an action of debt of 20 <abbr>l.</abbr>
               <note place="margin">8 E. 4.2.</note> and declare but a debt of 10 <abbr>l.</abbr> both ſhall abate.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="68"/>
               <hi>Contrariety.</hi> In treſpaſs <hi>de domo fracta &amp; muris ejuſdem domus fractis.</hi>
               <note place="margin">21 E. 4.36 4 E. 4.29. 21 <hi>H.</hi> 7.21 2 &amp; 3 P. &amp; M. 153.</note> The defendant cannot plead not-guilty to the breaking of the houſe, and juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the breaking of the walls, for houſe and walls are all one; and he cannot
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:170545:93"/>of the ſame thing both juſtifie and plead Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guilty, for by the juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he acknowledgeth himſelf guilty; ſo they are contrary.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="69"/>
               <hi>And therefore, It will not drive a man to juſtifie that he goeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to defeat:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0 <hi>H.</hi> 7.9.</note> He that bringeth an Aſſize of the Maſterſhip of a Chappell againſt <hi>J. S:</hi> ſhall not need to name <hi>J. S.</hi> the Maſter of the Chappell, becauſe the Plaintiſſe is to diſprove his intereſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Diligence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="70"/>
               <hi>It hateth folly and negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Litt. 95. 5 E. 3.222.</note> A diſcent caſt du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Coverture, where the wife is diſſeiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:170545:93"/>barreth her not of her entry after her husbands death; But if a Feme-ſole be diſſeized, and then ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a Husband, there a diſcent during the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verture taketh away her Entry; for it was her folly to take ſuch a Husband that entred not in time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Speeding of mens cauſes. And therefore,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="71"/>
               <hi>It hateth delayes.</hi> He that pleadeth a record in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay,<note place="margin">3 <hi>H.</hi> 6.15. 12 <hi>H.</hi> 7.3. 8 <hi>H.</hi> 7.9. 2 <hi>H.</hi> 6.1.</note> as to prove the Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiff excommunicate, muſt have it ready to ſhew; otherwiſe it is, if he plead it in bar.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="72"/>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nneceſſary circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</hi> One that is in Court ready to joyn with the Defendant,<note place="margin">8 <hi>H.</hi> 6.1. 1 <hi>H.</hi> 6.4.</note> may do it
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:170545:94"/>without proceſs. As the Vouchee the Plaintiffs leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor being praid in aid of, when the defendant in a replevin avoweth upon him, or the Meſne when the Lord Paramont avow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth upon him. But joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in aid cannot be by Attorney without pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="73"/>
               <hi>Circuit of action.</hi> Upon the grant of a ward with war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranty,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Manxel</hi>'s caſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7. <hi>b.</hi>
               </note> the Defendant in a writ of right of ward may rebutt the Plaintiſſ by that warranty, and ſhall not be driven to bring an action of covenant for avoiding circuit of action.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Law conſtrueth things with equity and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="151" facs="tcp:170545:94"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="74"/>
               <hi>And therefore,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſtraineth a general act if there be any miſchief or inconvenience in it.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Litt. 110.</note> Tenant for life lets to another for life without expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing whoſe lives, it ſhall be taken for the leſſors own life, for elſe it were a forfeiture of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="75"/>
               <hi>Moderateth the ſtrictneſs of the Law it ſelf.</hi> By a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridging, diminiſhing, and taking away the ſeverity of it, and mollifying the hardneſs of it, A morall vertue, as <hi>Plowden</hi> calleth it, and may appear by <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle,</hi> who treating of it defineth it, <hi>A certain cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Law, wherein it is any way wanting, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:170545:95"/>of the generality of it.</hi> It is no treſpaſs to carry away a mans wife againſt his will to a lawfull end. As to ſue a divorce againſt her Husband, or to have the peace of him before a Juſtice of Peace:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To the beſt. And therefore,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Every act to be lawfull when it ſtandeth indifferent to be lawful or not.</hi>
               <note place="margin">6 11 <hi>H.</hi> 7.5.</note> In an action of treſpaſſe, two iſſues are joyned triable in two Counties, One in <hi>London,</hi> another in <hi>Middleſex</hi> onely, without ſaying which of the iſſues it ſhould try, this ſhall be taken to try the iſſue in <hi>Middleſex</hi> onely: for ſo the <hi>venire facias</hi> is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:170545:95"/>and not in both Counties, which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Law. And therefore it is a diſcontinuance of the Iſſue in <hi>London,</hi> and not a miſ-continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus far of Rules drawn from their Sciences. There follow thoſe that are proper to our ſelves, which we call Law-conſtructions. And theſe are natural, or fained.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of the firſt ſort we have two notable grounds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Law conſtrueth things reaſonably.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore, With a reaſonable intent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> A bargain and fale of Land, and a reverſion, by deed not inrolled,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:170545:96"/>the Reverſion paſſeth not, no more then the Land,<note place="margin">21 H. 7.5.</note> though the Deed, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Inrolment, may paſs the Reverſion; but it was meant they ſhould paſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="78"/>
               <hi>According to the effect.</hi> A Deed delivered by an Infant,<note place="margin">1 H. 6.4.</note> cannot be delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red again at his full age; for, it took ſome effect before, and was but voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable. Otherwiſe, of a Feme Covert, or a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe of one that hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the land; for here the firſt delivery was meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly void.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="79"/>
               <hi>So that he that cannot have the effect of a thing, ſhall not have the thing it ſelf.</hi> The King ſhall not
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:170545:96"/>be received upon default of Tenant for life,<note place="margin">4 Eliz. 241.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Demandant cannot have the effect of the Receipt; <hi>viz.</hi> to count againſt him, which none can doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King, but ſue to him by Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="80"/>
               <hi>To the most validity.</hi> Tenant in tail,<note place="margin">Lit. 140. <hi>b.</hi>
               </note> makes a Leaſe for life; this ſhall be intended the Leſſee's life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="81"/>
               <hi>When any joyn in an act, it maketh it his act that may do it.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lit. 2 &amp; 7 El. Dy. 191.</note> The Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeizee, and the heir of the Diſſeizor, in by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, make a Feoffment by one Deed and Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:170545:97"/>this is the Feoffment of the Heir onely, and confirmation of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeizee.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="82"/>
               <hi>When two Titles con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur, the beſt is preferred.</hi> One is diſſeized,<note place="margin">Litt.</note> and the diſſeizor lets the land to the Diſſeizee for term of years, or at will: Now, if he enter, the Law ſhall ſay, he is in of his ancient and beſt ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="83"/>
               <hi>Things to be done by him that hath most skill to do them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">9 E. 4.4. 4 E. 6.15. 4 El. 230. Litt. 22.11 E. 4.36.</note> An Obligation upon Conditiou, that the Obligee ſhall bring to the Obligor's ſhop (being a Tailor) three yards of Cloth, which ſhall be ſhapen, and the
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:170545:97"/>Obligor to make the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligee a Gown of it; the Obligor muſt ſhape it. So, a Merchant agreeth with the King's Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, that his Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe ſhall be weighed at the Kings Beam, and the King ſhall have his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidie as it riſeth; the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector muſt weigh it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="84"/>
               <hi>Void things, good to ſome purpoſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">10 <hi>H.</hi> 7.12 1: &amp; 2. P. &amp; M<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 107.</note> A Feoffment up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Condition to be void, as if it had never been, yet the Feoffee ſhall have an Action of Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, after the Feoffor's entry, for the Condition broken, for a Treſpaſſe done by the Feoffor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="85"/>
               <hi>One thing to inure as
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:170545:98"/>another.</hi>
               <note place="margin">21 H. 7.3. 15 H. 7.7. 37 H. 6.4.</note> The King grants to a Town, <hi>eaſdem liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates quas</hi> London <hi>habet;</hi> it ſhall be intended the like, The Leſſor infeoff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his Leſſee for life, by <hi>Dedi, &amp; Conceſſi;</hi> this ſhall inure as a confimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="86"/>
               <hi>In one thing, all things purſuant to be included.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 R. 2. Bar. 309.</note> Upon a Grant of Trees, the Grantee may come upon the Land to cut them down, and with his carriage carry them tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the Land.<note place="margin">14 H. 8.1. 10 E. 3.17.</note> And the Vendee of all ones fiſhes in his pond, may juſtifie the comming upon the banks to fiſh, but not the digging of a trench to let out the water, to
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:170545:98"/>take the fiſh; for he might take them by Nets, and other devices. But if there were no other means to take them, he might dig a trench.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="87"/>
               <hi>Strongeſt againſt him that doth them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 &amp; 3. P. &amp; M. 140. <hi>b.</hi> 161. <hi>b.</hi>
               </note> Two Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants in common grant a Rent of 20 <abbr>s.</abbr> the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee ſhall have forty ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings. But if they reſerve twenty ſhillings upon a Leaſe, they ſhall have onely one twenty ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings.</p>
            <p>And therefore,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="88"/>
               <hi>A man ſhall not qualifie his own act.</hi> As,<note place="margin">21 H. 7.23. <hi>b.</hi>
               </note> if the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligee releaſeth his debt till <hi>Michaelmas,</hi> the debt is gone for ever. So, a reverſion of three acres
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:170545:99"/>of land is granted,<note place="margin">18 E. 3.53 17 Eliz. Dy. 339.</note> the tenant atturns for one; it is a good atturnment for all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The conſtruction which otherwiſe Law would make, is altered by the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="89"/>
               <hi>Special agreement.</hi> Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee for years is excuſed for waſte,<note place="margin">40 E. 3.5. Peck. 55.56.</note> if the houſes be blown down by ſudden ſtorm or tempeſts. But in that caſe, if he covenant to keep reparations, an acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of covenant lies againſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="90"/>
               <hi>Speciall words.</hi> As, a Leaſe reſerving a Rent,<note place="margin">27 <hi>H.</hi> 8.19 30 <hi>H.</hi> 8. Dy. 42. <hi>b.</hi>
               </note> the heir of the Leſſor, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his death, ſhall have the Rent: otherwiſe, if the Leaſe be reſerving to the Leſſor.</p>
            <pb n="161" facs="tcp:170545:99"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="91"/>
               <hi>Surpluſage of words:</hi> An information upon a Statute, made ſuch a day,<note place="margin">6 E. 6.84. 9 E. 4.28. <hi>h.</hi>
               </note> and the day is miſtaken, is nought, though he need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not to have recited the day.<note place="margin">9 El. Dy. 255. <hi>b.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A fained construction, which we call a fiction in Law, is, when in a ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinary ſort the Law con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrueth a thing otherwiſe, than it is in truth; and is of the perſon, thing, action, and the circumstances thereof, time, and place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of the perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="92"/>
               <hi>Things done by another, are as if they wert done by one's ſelfe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">27. <hi>H.</hi> 8.24.</note> A promiſe to one's wife, in conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a thing to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by the husband;
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:170545:100"/>if the husband, upon his comming home, agree and perform the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, he may plead this promiſe as made to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. So, if my ſervant ſell my goods, and I agree; I ſhall have an action of debt, ſuppoſing be bought of me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of the thing, we have theſe two Rules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="93"/>
               <hi>A thing that cometh in lieu of another,</hi>
               <note place="margin">18 E. 3. rec. in val. 26.48 E. 3 11.6 <hi>H.</hi> 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>to be as if it were the ſame.</hi> One ſhall recover in value againſt the heir, (upon the Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors Warranty) lands, which the heir took in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change for lands deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="94"/>
               <hi>A thing to be all one with that, whereunto it doth
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:170545:100"/>amount.</hi> The Maxime of a Baſtard eigne, is, that the mulier puiſne muſt make an entry upon him, or elſe he gaineth the right; yet, a continual claim, made by the <hi>mulier puiſue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">14 <hi>H.</hi> 4.9. 14 <hi>H.</hi> 8.13 5 <hi>H.</hi> 7.1.</note> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeth his right, for it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounteth to an Entry. So, a Leaſe for years, and a Releaſe, amount to a Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="65"/>
               <hi>A thing that ſhould not be done; to be as if it were not done.</hi>
               <note place="margin">20 El. Dyer. 362.18 El. Dyer. 362.</note> A man makes a Leaſe for years of a houſe, with certain implements, reſerving a Rent. The Executors, after the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtators death, receive the Rent, yet it is no aſſetts in their hands; for the
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:170545:101"/>whole Rent belongeth to the Heir.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="69"/>
               <hi>So, of a thing done in a time that it ſhould not.</hi> A man ſeized in fee, lets for ten years,<note place="margin">1 E. <hi>b.</hi> Br. 18.</note> and after ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the land, and taketh it back to him and his wife; and then the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and wife let it for 20 years, reſerving a Rent. The husband dieth, the wife accepts this rent, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the firſt ten yeares. By this, the ſecond Leaſe is not affirmed,<note place="margin">21 El. 563.</note> for the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of a Rent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Leaſe beginneth, and ſo before any Rent be due, is no acceptance at all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To the circumſtance of Time, theſe two Rules per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="165" facs="tcp:170545:101"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Priority of time is ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined in things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="97"/>
               <hi>Done together.</hi> One de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſeth a term for years to his ſon,<note place="margin">21 El. 540.</note> and that the wife ſhall have it during the ſon's minority. This is firſt a Deviſe to his wife, and after to the ſon when he cometh of full age.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="98"/>
               <hi>Happening in an inſtant.</hi> A Meſualty deſcends to the Tenant of the Land:<note place="margin">11 <hi>H.</hi> 7.12 7 <hi>H.</hi> 46. 9 E. 4.21.</note> Though the Meſualty be at the ſame time and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant extinct; yet the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant ſhall pay relief, if he be of full age; or be in Ward, if he be within age; <hi>viz.</hi> where it is holden by Knights ſervice.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="99"/>
               <hi>Things relating to a time long before, be,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Litt. 92.36 <hi>H.</hi> 6.7.</note> 
               <hi>as if they were done immediately
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:170545:102"/>from that time.</hi> Where the wife is endowed by the heir of the husband's lands, ſhe ſhall be ſaid to be in, immediately from the husband. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if the husband were a Diſſeizor, and the heir in by diſcent; yet the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeizee may enter upon the wife.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe Rules of common reaſon do many times croſs and encounter one aenother, which is the greatest diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty that is found in the arguing of Caſes. But, to help this, the generall ground is, according to the former Rule, that,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="110"/>
               <hi>Thoſe prevail,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Litt. 110. <hi>b.</hi> 140. <hi>b.</hi> 32 <hi>H.</hi> 8.</note> 
               <hi>that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the more excellent and perfect reaſon with them.</hi> Tenant for life makes a
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:170545:102"/>Leaſe for life,<note place="margin">Br. gar. 18.28. E. 3.20 <hi>b.</hi> Br. gar. 17.35 <hi>H.</hi> 6.3. 9 El. Dy. 264. <hi>b.</hi> 11 <hi>H.</hi> 7.9. Perk. 41.13 <hi>H.</hi> 8.15.7. H. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.9.</note> without na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming whoſe life; this ſhall be intended for his own life, (<hi>Rule</hi> 74.) for elſe it were a wrong. But if Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in tail make ſuch a Leaſe for life, this is a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continuance, and for life of the Grantee, (<hi>Rule</hi> 86.) for it is ſtrongeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Grantor, and moſt beneficiall for the Grantee.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:170545:103"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170545:103"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
